<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions on that part of Mr. Robert Ferguson's book entituled The interest of reason in religion which treats of justification in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13683601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13683601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 830:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions on that part of Mr. Robert Ferguson's book entituled The interest of reason in religion which treats of justification in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 106 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by William Allen.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferguson, Robert, d. 1714. --  Interest of reason in religion.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101330:1"/>
            <p>Animadverſions On that part of Mr. <hi>ROBERT FERG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SON'S</hi> BOOK, Entituled, The <hi>INTEREST</hi> of REASON IN RELIGION, Which Treats of JUSTIFICATION: In a LETTER to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:101330:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101330:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Return you with Mr. <hi>Fergu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's</hi> Book my hearty thanks for the Loan of it. I have read it, and find many things well ſaid in it. And where I find anything otherwiſe, I impute it not to his want of ability if the Cauſe would bear it; but the Cauſe it ſelf in thoſe particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which I ſuſpect him to be defective in. For neither he nor any other, of what ability ſoever he be, can, as Solomon ſayes, <hi>make that ſtreight which God hath made crooked,</hi> Eccles. 7.13. And therefore the greater the parts be of any man, who yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make work of a Cauſe he undertakes, it doth but make me ſo much the more doubtfull of the goodneſs of that Cauſe, if it were any whit doubtfull to me before.</p>
            <p>I will give you one inſtance of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of Mr. <hi>Ferguſon's</hi> book, Chap. 2, Sect 10. Where he aſſerts that Mr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Notion (as he calls it) of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>is not any wayes maintainable but by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting innumerable texts from their plain and naturall Senſe to a Metaphorick: and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101330:3"/>that it is accompanied with this fatall unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of turning agreat part of the Bible into mere inſignificant and empty Metaphors.</hi> P. 402. 403. And then repreſents Mr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock's</hi> notion thus. <hi>That we are only juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by believing and obeying the Goſpel of Chriſt. That the Sacrifice of Chriſt's death and the Righteouſneſs of his life have no other influence upon our acceptance with God, but that to them we owe the Covenant of Grace: That is, God being well pleaſed with the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt's life and the Sacrifice of his death, entered into a new Covenant with mankind, wherein he promiſeth pardon of Sin and eternal life to thoſe who believe and obey the Goſpel. So that the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not the formal cauſe of our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, but the Righteouſneſs of his life and death is the Meritorious Cauſe whereby we are declared Righteous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded as Righteous perſons. The Covenant of Grace, which God for Chriſts ſake hath made, pardoning our paſt ſins and follies, and rewarding a ſincere though imperfect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Goſpel by its great arguments and motives and powerfull aſſiſtances, forms our minds to the love and practice of Holineſs, and ſo makes us inherently righteous: and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101330:3"/>Grace of the Goſpel accepts and rewards that ſincere Obedience, which according to the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and Severity of the Law could deſerve no reward.</hi> P. 404.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ferguſon</hi> having made this recital out of Mr. <hi>Sherlock's</hi> book, knew not how as it ſeems to make good his charge there-from; unleſs Mr. S. would be ſo kind as to grant what Mr. F. doth affirm, but Mr. S. him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf no where aſſerts. And therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he grants in P. 416. <hi>That in reſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the mere demands of the Goſpel we may in a proper ſenſe be ſaid to be juſtified; Yet he ſaith that in reference to the Law, which is that alone which accuſeth us, we cannot in any prepriety of ſpeech be ſaid to be juſtified, but that juſtification, whereſoever it regards our diſcharge from the accuſation of the Law, muſt be taken Metaphorically;</hi> (he meanes I ſuppoſe) unleſs we are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from that accuſation by having the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us. Whether this be true or no, I ſhall put to the Tryal afterwards.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time, pray you conſider how little reaſon Mr. F. had to go about to charge Mr. S. with holding Juſtification in a <hi>Metaphorick</hi> ſenſe, unleſs he had firſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101330:4"/>us, that according to M.<hi>S's</hi> ſentiment of Juſtification before repreſented, he had made ſomthing elſe neceſſary to it, than that which is an anſwering of the demands of the Goſpel, which yet he hath not done that I can ſee. But indeed M. F. is ſo far from doing that, as that he hath done the quite contrary, as you cannot but perceive, when you compare Mr. F's conceſſion and Mr. S<hi>'s</hi> notion touching Juſtification together: for Mr. F. acknowledgeth, as I ſaid before, that in reference to the mere demands of the Goſpel we may in a proper ſenſe be ſaid to be Juſtified; and M. S. ſaith no more, as M. F. recites him, but that we are only Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by believing and obeying the Goſpel. And if to believe and obey the Goſpel be not to anſwer the demands of the Goſpel and no more, pray you get Mr. F. to tell us what is. But if it be, then Mr. F. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making good his charge againſt M. S. hath himſelf even fairly acquitted and diſcharged him from it, and might well have taken himſelf off here, and ſaved himſelf the labour of further proſecution.</p>
            <p>But however, though M. S. doth not, yet it ſeems Mr. F. doth hold, that we muſt be Juſtified, if Juſtified, at all, by anſwering the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101330:4"/>demands of the Law as well, as of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, although the Scipture tells us that <hi>he that abideth in the Doctrine of</hi> Chriſt (which is the Goſpel) <hi>he hath both the Father and the Son. Rep. Jo.</hi> 9. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mr. <hi>F.</hi> is of opinion that the demands of the Law muſt be anſwered or elſe we cannot be Juſtified, therefore he thinks Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ought to be ſo too, which if he can perſwade him to be, then he doubts not, but that he ſhall be able to make good his charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>And therefore to lay a foundation for a neceſſity of a perfect legal Righteouſneſs unto Juſtification, though not inherent in our ſelves, yet by derivation of it from our Saviour, in whom it was, he does in effect aſſert the Original Legal Covenant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill in force, notwithſtanding the eſtabliſhing with men the Evangelical: and that in order to our Juſtification, it is not enough to have an Evangelical Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to anſwer the demands of the Goſpel, but that we muſt alſo have a perfect legal Righteouſneſs to anſwer the demands of the Law, though not in our ſelves but, by derivation from another, as was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101330:5"/>
            <p>Whether this be not ſo, judge, I pray you, by his own words, comparing what he ſayes in P. 411. and P. 414. which are theſe. <hi>Now as the introduction of the law of faith hath not abrogated the law of perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but this as well as that doth remain in force, each of them requiring a conformity to its own demands: So ſuppoſing us to anſwer all that the Goſpel requires, yet the other law abiding uncancelled, and we being all guilty of the violation of its terms, there lies accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly a charge againſt us, from which by Juſtification we are to be acquitted. p.</hi> 414. <hi>And again p.</hi> 411. <hi>That ſecluding not only the righteouſneſs of Chriſt's life, but the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his death as the</hi> Matter, <hi>and the imputation of it as</hi> the formal <hi>Cauſe of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, it ſeems repugnant to the immutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and eſſentiall Holineſs of God, to juſtifie us upon an imperfect obedience, the Law which requireth a perfect remaining ſtill in force, and denouncing wrath in caſe of every failure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which you will perceive, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that Mr. <hi>F.</hi> holds that the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in force, requiring a perfect obedience unto juſtification, and for want thereof and in caſe of every failure, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101330:5"/>wrath. And that therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſ the ſatisfaction of Chriſt's death and the righteouſneſs of his life were formally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, (<hi>ie.</hi> (as I ſuppoſe he meanes) ſo as that we may be ſaid to have made ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in and by him, and perfectly kept the Law in and by him by having his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſatisfaction imputed to us) it would be repugnant to the immutability and eſſentiall Holineſs of God to juſtifie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an imperfect Obedience.</p>
            <p>In which aſſertions of his there ſeem to me to be two grand miſtakes, beſides that of a formal imputation he ſpeaks of. The firſt is in holding the law to be ſtill in force, not only in requiring obedience to it ſelf by way of <hi>Duty,</hi> which is true, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring <hi>perfection</hi> of Obedience as a <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Juſtification, and in its <hi>Rigor</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity in denouncing wrath in caſe of <hi>every failure.</hi> Secondly, In that he holds, that though we ſhould anſwer all that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel requires both in reſpect of a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of inherent Grace, and of a perſonal ſincere obedience, yet we could not be juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified without the formal imputation of a perfect legal righteouſneſs, as aforeſaid, and that theſe two are grand miſtakes indeed, I ſhall endeavor to demonſtrate to you.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101330:6"/>
            <p>In oppoſition to the firſt of them, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Scripture will warrant me to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That God by founding <hi>a new</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a Covenant of <hi>Grace,</hi> with the world in his Son Jeſus Chriſt and his Mediatory undertaking, hath <hi>Reſcinded</hi> or Superſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Rigour and ſeverity of the original Law in two things. Firſt as a legal perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of obedience was by it required as the <hi>Condition</hi> of Juſtification and life: And Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as it did <hi>denounce</hi> wrath and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation in caſe of <hi>every failure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the original Law of nature, the moral Law be eternal and unchangeable in requiring obedience by way of <hi>Duty,</hi> yet it is not ſo in the foreſaid Rigour and ſeverity of its Sanction.</p>
            <p>To eſtabliſh the Law again in this ſenſe after the Covenant of Promiſe is made, would be according to the Apoſtle's reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>make faith void, and the Promiſe of none effect. Rom.</hi> 4.14. Gal. 3.18. For the old and new terms of Juſtification can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt together, without the one eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuating the other. <hi>If by Grace</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>then is it no more of works: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Grace would be no more Grace. But if of works, then it is no more Grace; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101330:6"/>work is no more work.</hi> Ro. 11.6. And again, <hi>whoſoever of you are juſtified by the law ye are fallen from Grace,</hi> Gal. 5.4. By the interpoſition of Chriſt we are <hi>redeemed</hi> from the Sanction or <hi>Curſe of the Law,</hi> which curſeth every one that continueth not in all things which it requireth, and that for this very end, <hi>that the bleſſing of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (viz. of being Juſtified by faith accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the terms of the new Covenant) <hi>might come on the Gentiles through Jeſus Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.13, 14. Intimating, that this bleſſing of the new Covenant could not have taken place, if the Curſe of the old had ſtill remained.</p>
            <p>When St. Paul ſaith, that <hi>the Miniſtration of Death written &amp; engraven in ſtones is done away</hi> (2 Cor. 3, 7. Compared with v. 11.) I pray you what of this was done away by the Introduction of the Evangelical miniſtration, if not the <hi>Rigour</hi> of the <hi>Condition</hi> of eſcaping the Curſe of it? For from that it is that it is denominated the Miniſtration of Death and Condemnation, and it is done away as ſuch a Miniſtration. For otherwiſe the Law en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in ſtones, as it is a Rule of and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Duty, is not done away: In this ſenſe indeed Chriſt <hi>did not come to deſtroy the Law,</hi> Mat. 5.17.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101330:7"/>
            <p>This benefit by Chriſt in God's making a new Covenant and granting new terms, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of his undertaking, is not limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome men only, but extended to all. In this ſenſe Chriſt died for all men without exception. And it is not unlikely, but that one reaſon at leaſt, why God in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodneſs thought it meet to vouchſafe unto the whole race of Adam theſe new and gracious terms of recovery after the fall, when no ſuch thing is granted the lapſed Angels, was this, becauſe the Condemnation, into which the Angels fell, was by their own perſonal actuall rebellion without Temptation from another; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Condemnation, into which all the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> fell, proceeded originally from his and his wives tranſgreſſion, (and that from the temptation of the Devil) and not from the perſonal act of their Progeny.</p>
            <p>And that the benefit of freeing men from the Rigorous Sanction of the Law by the active and paſſive obedience of Chriſt, in which the new Covenant is founded, is as extenſive, as ever the effect of Adam's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience was in ſubjecting all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation according to the Rigorous terms of the Law, is I conceive plainly aſſerted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101330:7"/>by the Apoſtle, when he ſaith in Rom. 5.18. <hi>as by the Offence of One Judgement came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men to Condemnation: even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of One the free gift came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men unto Juſtification of life.</hi> By the <hi>free gift,</hi> which comes by the Righteouſnes of Chriſt upon all men unto Juſtification of life, I underſtand the <hi>New Covenant.</hi> For this free gift can neither be the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the One here ſpoken of, but that which is procured by it, Nor yet juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication it ſelf, for that is the effect of it. So that we cannot in reaſon underſtand it otherwiſe than of ſome middle thing, and that in all probability can be none other than the <hi>Grace</hi> contained in the <hi>New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which Covenant God by a moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious graunt and free gift hath vouchſafed to all men for the Righteouſneſs ſake of Chriſt here ſpoken of, in which remiſſion of Sin and eternal life are promiſed upon condition of faith. And this exactly agrees with what the ſame Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. when he ſaith that <hi>by Grace we are ſaved through faith, and that not of our ſelves, it is the</hi> gift <hi>of God:</hi> that is, it is the Grace and gift of God, that now we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by faith; a favour which the Law ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101330:8"/>afforded; for the <hi>Law is not of faith, but the man that doth them ſhall live in them.</hi> And when the Apoſtle ſaith this free gift came upon all men unto juſtification of life, we are not to underſtand it, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as if Juſtification in <hi>act</hi> came upon all men univerſally by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt and this free gift, but that for the ſake of the one and in the other, ſuch gracious <hi>terms</hi> are granted and offered to <hi>all men</hi> without exception, as by which they <hi>may attain</hi> unto juſtification of life <hi>actually,</hi> if they do not wilfully <hi>neglect and reject</hi> them. And leſs than this I ſee not how the Apoſtle's words can ſignifie, if you conſider the nature of the Compariſon he makes between the effects of the firſt Adam's diſobedience and the ſecond Adam's obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in reference unto all men without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of any. As by the diſobedience of the former all men were brought under an utter incapacity of being juſtified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo long as the original Covenant in the Rigour of its Sanction remained in force, So by the obedience of the latter all men are put into a capacity of being juſtified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by vertue of new terms in the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which are obtained thereby, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101330:8"/>by which the old terms are Cancelled or Superſeded.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo, I leave you to judge whether there be any need of or any <hi>occaſion</hi> for ſuch a formal imputation of Chriſt's righteouſneſs unto our juſtification to anſwer the Law in its demands of perfect legal obedience as a condition of it, and the accuſations thereof for want of it, as Mr. <hi>F.</hi> contends for and Mr. <hi>S.</hi> oppoſeth For this demand and this accuſation was taken off ſo ſoon as the new Covenant founded by God in Chriſt's active and paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence took place. And this benefit of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>new terms</hi> of life granted, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues to the world by Chriſt's Mediatory undertaking, does not at all depend upon our believing in Chriſt, but is <hi>abſolutely free,</hi> and that wherein he hath been aforehand with us and with all men which have been born into the world ſince the Covenant of Grace did firſt commence, and remains made good to them whether they beleive it or no. So that from thence forth no man ſhall be condemned for want of a perfect le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Righteouſneſs, but only for want of an Evangelical righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this is a matter of weight,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101330:9"/>I will add yet ſomthing further to prove, that this new Covenant, by which the terms of the old are cancel'd, is made and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht in Chriſt, not only with ſome part of mankind, <hi>viz.</hi> Such as ſhall be ſaved, as ſome would reſtrain it (who think it in the nature of it abſolute and not condito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, no not in reference to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which yet it muſt needs be, if made to all, unleſs all were eventually to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) but it's made with all men univerſally. And to this purpoſe I pray you conſider the declaration of God's grace and favour to all mankind in thoſe words of his to Abraham Iſaac and Jacob, mentioned no leſs than five times in the book of Geneſis, <hi>viz. In thee and in thy Seed ſhall all families, all Nations of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Chap. 12.3. and 18.18. and 22.18. and 26.4. and 28.14. By which the unbelieving Jews indeed underſtood, that in time all Nations ſhould become proſelytes to Judaiſm, and their Nation become the head of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Meſſias a glorious viſible head over them. But in oppoſition hereto and to their expectations of Juſtification by the Law, St. Paul interprets it to be meant of the Covenant of Grace eſtabliſhed in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101330:9"/>Chriſt with all Nations and Families of the Earth, who are all ſo far bleſſed hereby, as to have new-terms of Salvation granted them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. For, whereas they underſtood by ſeed the whole poſterity of <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob's</hi> line, as if all Nations ſhould be bleſſed in them; St. <hi>Paul</hi> reſtrains it only to Chriſt, as all Nations were to be bleſt in him, as head of the Covenant <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. <hi>He ſaith not unto Seeds as of many, but as of one, and to thy Seed which is Chriſt.</hi> And then that the bleſſing promiſed to all Nations in this Seed was the Covenant, appeares by the next words in <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>And this I ſay, that the Covenant, which was confirmed before of God in Chriſt, the Law which was</hi> 430 <hi>years after cannot diſanull, that it ſhould make the promiſe of none effect.</hi> This Covenant we ſee was then <hi>confirmed</hi> of God in Chriſt, not then firſt <hi>made,</hi> for it was extant in the world before. And to the ſame ſenſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid before in <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, foreſeeing that God would juſtifie the heathen through Faith, preached before the Goſpel unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>ſaying, in thee ſhall all Nations be bleſſed.</hi> And when he ſaith, that God in thoſe words preached the <hi>Goſpel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it is all one as to have ſaid he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101330:10"/>declared to him the <hi>Covenant,</hi> for Goſpel here and Covenant in <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. are two words indeed, but ſignifie the ſame thing, as frequently they do elſewhere. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> expreſly calls that promiſe to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the <hi>Covenant. Acts</hi> 3.25. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares what the nature and ſubſtance of that Covenant or Goſpel was, which is extended to all Nations in that promiſe, and that, he ſayes, was, that God would <hi>juſtifie the heathen through Faith;</hi> which is a breif deſcription of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace. Theſe things then being ſo, that God hath eſtabliſhed a new Covenant with all men, and thereby cancelled the Rigorous Sanction of the Primitive Law, as that required <hi>perfection</hi> of Obedience as the <hi>Condition</hi> of Juſtification, I now leave you to judge whether Mr. <hi>F.</hi> doth not build the neceſſity of the imputation of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto Juſtification in the ſenſe he aſſerts it neceſſary, upon an imaginary foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and groundleſs Suppoſition, and if he do, that foundation being removed, that which he builds thereon muſt needs fall.</p>
            <p>Having I hope, Sir, by this time ſatisfied you, and clearly evinced, that I have not without cauſe charged Mr. <hi>F.</hi> with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101330:10"/>of the two grand miſtakes above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, I ſhall now proceed to endeavour to do the like touching the Second, which Second, as you may remember, was in that he holds that although we ſhould <hi>anſwer all that the Goſpel requires,</hi> both in reſpect of a righteouſnes of <hi>inherent Grace,</hi> and of perſonal <hi>ſincere obedience,</hi> yet we could not be juſtified without ſuch a <hi>perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> imputed to us, and derived upon us, as would adequately <hi>anſwer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and accuſations of the Law.</hi> That thus he holds is evident by what he ſayes in <hi>p.,</hi> 414. and in other paſſages in the ſame Section.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need here to do again what I have done already, that is; to prove the non-neceſſity of the imputation of ſuch a righteouſneſs unto us for our Juſtification, as every way anſwers the demands of the Law, as conſidered in its originall Rigour and ſeverity. That which remains for me to do, is to demonſtrate to you, that M. <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſon</hi> is under a miſtake in denying that our anſwering all that the Goſpel requires in a righteouſneſs both of inherent Grace and perſonal ſincere obedience, is a vailable to juſtification, without the imputation of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101330:11"/>Chriſt's righteouſneſs in Mr. <hi>F</hi>'s ſenſe, and withall to ſhew that we are ſaid in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſenſe to be juſtified by believing and obeying the Goſpel; and that <hi>Mr. F.</hi> had neither ground nor fair pretence to charge <hi>Mr. S</hi>'s ſentiment of being juſtified by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and obeying the Goſpel, with any ſuch abſurdity or inconvenience, as that it is not maintainable without perverting innumerable texts from their plain and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſenſe to a Metaphorick.</p>
            <p>Only let me premiſe this, that it would alwayes be remembred, that whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits do accrue to us by vertue of the new Covenant, are owing unto Chriſt and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributable unto him, in whom, for whoſe ſake, and upon account of whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking the Covenant it ſelf, and all the benefits of it are vouchſafed unto men. And accordingly this Covenant in Scripture is ſaid to be <hi>confirmed of God in Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.17. to be the <hi>new-Teſtament in his blood,</hi> Mat. 26.28. and his blood to be <hi>the blood of the everlaſting Covenant,</hi> Heb. 13.20. And he himſelf <hi>given for a Covenant of the People,</hi> Iſ. 42.6. and <hi>all the promiſes of God are in him yea, and in him amen.</hi> 2. Cor. 1.22. What ever then depends
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101330:11"/>upon this Covenant, depends upon Chriſt, and accordingly the benefits promiſed in it, Remiſſion of ſin, and eternal life are in Scripture aſcribed unto him. And although Faith, as comprehending repentance and ſincere obedience, be imputed for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, yet it is not for its own ſake that it is ſo, but for Chriſt's ſake, and all by vertue of the divine will which hath of mere Grace and favour appointed that ſo it ſhall be.</p>
            <p>This being premiſed, I proceed now to ſhew, that we are juſtified by God upon our believing and obeying the Goſpel, and that in a proper ſenſe, and that our belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and obeying the Goſpel is our Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical righteouſneſs; upon the taking place whereof in men, God accounts, and by the doctrine in the Scriptures declares them juſt, and deals with them accordingly, which is his juſtifying of them.</p>
            <p>To this end let it be conſidered, that this Covenant, as founded by God in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt's life, and Sacrifice of his death, doth conſiſt of two parts, of <hi>Conditions</hi> required by God, and to be performed by men; and of <hi>promiſe</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits made by God and to be performed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101330:12"/>by him, but to be received and enjoyed by men. The <hi>Condition,</hi> upon which promiſe of benefits is made by God, is that which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> rightly calls a <hi>believing and obeying</hi> the Goſpel. And the <hi>benefits</hi> promiſed upon the aforeſaid condition, Mr. <hi>S.</hi> truly ſaith are <hi>pardon of Sin and eternal life.</hi> That ſuch promiſes are made and upon ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, appears every where in Scripture, where things of this nature are ſpoken of, as every one knows, that knows the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and Mr. <hi>F.</hi> himſelf ſtands declared no enemy to the Doctrine of the conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality of the promiſes.</p>
            <p>Things then being thus ſetled between God and all men in this Covenant, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry upon every man's tryall will be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath performed the condition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired on his part in believing, repenting, and ſincerely obeying. If it be found that he hath, he is thereupon as truly and in a proper Senſe juſtified, that is accounted and by the Goſpel declared and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Evangelically juſt and righteous, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the ſenſe of this Evangelicall Law, as he would have been in the ſenſe of the Original Law, in caſe he had obſerved the terms of that.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101330:12"/>
            <p>And had I been to have written to Mr <hi>F.</hi> I would have enquired of him, which of theſe things now mentioned he would or could deny, being all ſo perfectly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as they are, to the tenour and very letter of the Scripture? Will he, or can he deny belief in the Goſpel, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it to be the Condition, upon which God in the Goſpel or new Covenant hath promiſed pardon of Sin and eternal life? or, which is the ſame, that he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theſe benefits to ſuch and to no other?</p>
            <p>This I take for granted he will not deny.</p>
            <p>Next I would demand whether Faith, Repentance and ſincere obdience, be not all that is required of men themſelves by God in the Goſpel to make them Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally righteous, and capable of the ſaving benefits promiſed in the Goſpel? If they be (and I believe Mr. <hi>F.</hi> will not deny them to be ſo, from one of his own aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>p.</hi> 414.) then I further query, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe do not denominate a man Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically righteous, or righteous in the goſpel ſenſe, as well as the doing all that the Law required would have denominated a man legally righteous, or righteous in the ſenſe of the Law?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101330:13"/>
            <p>And further whether men from thoſe qualifications aforeſaid, are not in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo denominated? As for inſtance, <hi>Faith,</hi> which is, as I have ſaid, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of repentance and ſincere obedience when ſaveing, this, as the Scripture tells us expreſly, <hi>was counted to</hi> Abraham <hi>for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 4.3. Gal. 3.6. And we are told alſo; that the Scripture, ſpeaking of this in reference to <hi>Abraham, was not written for his ſake only, but for us alſo to whom it ſhall be imputed if we believe on him, who raiſed up</hi> Jeſus <hi>our</hi> Lord <hi>from the dead.</hi> verſ. 23.24.</p>
            <p>And then for Evangelical or ſincere obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that comes in alſo for a ſhare in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominating a man righteous, in a goſpel ſenſe: <hi>He that doth righteouſneſs is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. John,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.7. and he ſpeaks it of that righteouſneſs which men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do in a courſe of ſincere obedience, and not of the righteouſneſs of another im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them. <hi>In the righteouſneſs which</hi> he <hi>hath done</hi> ſhall he <hi>live</hi> ſaith the <hi>Phophet,</hi> ſpeaking of a man that ſhall turn from all the ſins which he hath committed, and ſhall <hi>obſerve all God's Statutes, and do all that which is lawfull and right,</hi> Ezek. 18.22. If
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101330:13"/>then Faith, Repentance and ſincere obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, be all that the goſpel requires to denominate a man righteous in a goſpel ſenſe, and to make him capable of the promiſed benefits, Then all thoſe in whom theſe are found, are by God in the Goſpel declared and pronounced righteous men; which Declaration is their Juſtification: For what is done in this kind by the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel on Earth, is done alſo by God in Heaven.</p>
            <p>No man ſure that underſtands and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders what he ſaith, will deny this to be Juſtification in a proper ſenſe, nor aſſert it not maintainable without perverting the ſcriptures from their plain and natural mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to a <hi>Metaphorick</hi> ſenſe, whereas its moſt evident, it ſtands back't with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, underſtood in their plain proper and genuine ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>Mr. Ferguſon</hi> was ſomwhat ſenſible, that he could not duly infer any thing from <hi>Mr. S's</hi> own words, touching his apprehenſions about Juſtification, but what was agreeable to the Notion of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in a proper ſenſe, in reference to the demands of the goſpel, as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by what he ſaith towards the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101330:14"/>of the page 416. And becauſe he had a great mind to faſten ſomthing by way of retortion upon <hi>Mr. S's</hi> Notion of Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, as if it had not been maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be Juſtification properly ſo called, without wreſting the Scriptures from their plain and proper ſenſe, (which was the the thing <hi>Mr. S.</hi> charged on them, whoſe opinion <hi>Mr. F.</hi> undertakes to defend;) therefore <hi>Mr. F.</hi> inſinuates to his Reader that <hi>Mr. S's</hi> Notion doth imply (unleſs he will allow that we are Juſtified by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made righteous by the perfect Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us,) ſuch a Juſtification, as cannot be properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nor maintained to be ſuch, without perverting the Scriptures from their plain and proper ſenſe, to that which is but ſo Metaphorically. And to this end he takes it for granted that Juſtification in <hi>Mr. S's</hi> Notion of it, contains in it <hi>remiſſion of Sins;</hi> and then argues that remiſſion of Sin is not Juſtification in a proper ſenſe, and conſequently that <hi>Mr. S's</hi> Notion of juſtification cannot be made good from the Scriptures, without underſtanding them in an improper ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Mr. F.</hi> would have done this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101330:14"/>buſineſs indeed againſt <hi>Mr. S.</hi> he ſhould have done one of theſe two things, which yet he hath not done. Either firſt ſhewed that <hi>Mr. S.</hi> hath defined juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by pardon of ſin, or Secondly, that according to his Notion of it, it muſt be ſo defined; neither of which he hath done that I finde. And therefore he doth but beat the air, while he would have his Reader think he is beating <hi>Mr. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That pardon of ſin is promiſed in the Covenant of Grace to thoſe that believe and obey the Goſpel, <hi>Mr. S.</hi> doth indeed aſſert, and that according to the Scriptures: and this pardon, when vouchſafed, doth diſcharge us from whatever lay againſt us, either from Law or Goſpel, and is called in Scripture a not mentioning our ſins unto us, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.16. the remembring them no more, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.17. a not imputing of them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.8. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. but then theſe are two diſtinct things, to juſtifie a perſon againſt an accuſation of not belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and obeying the Goſpel, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring upon him the benefits promiſed to thoſe that have. If they be not different, but one and the ſame thing, then the <hi>giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of eternal</hi> life it ſelf, is an aſſentiall part
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101330:15"/>of our juſtification as well as the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our ſins, for that as well as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſins is promiſed to thoſe who believe and obey the Goſpel. And I think no man yet ever aſſerted, that the giving of eternal life was juſtification it ſelf, but a benefit promiſed to thoſe who are juſtified, according to St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Whom he Juſtified, them he alſo glorified:</hi> Juſtification is God's <hi>imputing righteouſneſs</hi> to men, or their faith to them for righteouſneſs: and thus <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by having his faith imputed to him for righteouſneſs. But pardon of ſin is his <hi>not imputing to them their Treſpaſſes:</hi> and I muſt needs ſay, I cannot apprehend how the imputation of faith for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the non-imputation of ſin can be all one.</p>
            <p>God in juſtifing men, avoucheth and pronounceth them to be ſuch as to whome he hath promiſed pardon, that is true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſuch as have performed the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the promiſe. But then the counting of this performance of the condition for righteouſneſs unto them is one thing, and the conferring on them the benefit promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on that condition is another, as I ſaid.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101330:15"/>If God had promiſed pardon only upon account of what Chriſt hath done and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Sinners, without any condition to be performed on their part, then they would have had title to pardon without the juſtification I ſpeak of: But ſince it is otherwiſe, a man's title to pardon is not cleared without being <hi>juſtified</hi> in order thereto, <hi>as a performer of the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover the <hi>clearing the equity</hi> of God's proceeding in pardoning ſome, and not other ſome, depends upon this, <hi>viz.</hi> That he can juſtifie one ſort to be ſuch as have repented, and performed the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on which he promiſed pardon; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he cannot do ſo concerning the other. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. And when I conſider this, I cannot ſee, but that we have as much reaſon to think it meet and neceſſary, that there ſhould be ſuch a difference between juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and pardon as hath been intimated, as there is to believe, that its fit and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that the reaſon and equity of god's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſhould be cleared before <hi>Angels</hi> and men, in pardoning ſome and not oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And if this be found agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then you have an evidence from the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101330:16"/>reaſon and nature of the thing why it ſhould be ſo, as well as from the Scriptures to ſhew that it is ſo.</p>
            <p>Yet its very true alſo, that there is ſo very cloſe and inſeparable a connexion between Juſtification and Remiſſion of Sin, as that the Scripture (which does not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes nicely difference things which yet are diſtinguiſhable, but ſometimes terms things by the ſame name, which differ only but in ſome reſpect, and ſometimes denotes things of the ſame nature, by different phraſes and forms of ſpeech,) I ſay the connexion between Juſtification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is ſo cloſe and inſeparable, as that the Scripture ſometimes ſpeakes of them promiſcuouſly, ſcarcely leaving any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to be diſcerned between them; which I conceive hath led ſo many to place Juſtification in Remiſſion of Sin, as are of that Judgement.</p>
            <p>Such is <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6, 7. for one, where <hi>the bleſſedneſs of the man, to whom God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth Righteouſneſs without works, is</hi> thus <hi>deſcribed by</hi> David, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing his words, ſaying,: <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered.</hi> Where you will hardly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101330:16"/>any difference made between the imputation of Righteouſnes, and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sins, unleſs we diſtinguiſh between righteouſneſs imputed, and the bleſſedneſs of haveing ſin pardoned as conſecuent upon it; which I think may very well be done. For the Apoſtle doth not ſay, that <hi>David</hi> deſcribes the <hi>Juſtification</hi> of the man to whom God imputeth righteouſneſs withont works, when he ſaith, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven; but the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> of ſuch a perſon who is ſo juſtified, or to whom righteouſneſs is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. Which bleſſedneſs he placeth in the forgiveneſs of ſins, and being reſtored to the Divine favour. So that theſe words of <hi>David,</hi> as I ſaid, are not a <hi>deſcription</hi> of Juſtification, but of the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> a man comes to be poſſeſſed of by being juſtified. The reaſon and deſign of the Apoſtle in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing theſe words of <hi>David,</hi> I ſhall ſhew afterwards.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. is another ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where it's ſaid, that <hi>by him all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are juſtified from all things, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> Where to be juſtified, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the deſert of ſin, ſeem to be
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101330:17"/>the ſame: Unleſs you will diſtinguiſh (as well you may) between that <hi>from</hi> which we are delivered, to wit, the obligation to Puniſhment, and that <hi>by</hi> meanes whereof we come ſo to be delivered, to wit, our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtified: and then to be juſtified from thoſe things, ſignifies no more here, than by juſtification to come to be pardoned and ſo delivered from condemnation.</p>
            <p>But if you will underſtand Juſtification in a large ſenſe, as comprehending and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in with it its effects, (in which ſenſe faith it ſelfe is oft to be underſtood,) then indeed it includes pardon of ſin: and then in this ſenſe to be pardoned is to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and to be juſtified is to be pardoned. In which ſenſe or reſpect it may be it is, that many renowned both Perſons and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, have made little or no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Juſtification and remiſſion of ſin.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> if what I have ſuggeſted have any weight in it, (which I ſubmit to tryal) then you may ſee, that there is a Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of believers properly ſo called, plainly and without figure aſſerted in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet not conſiſting in that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Righteouſneſs neither, which Mr. <hi>F.</hi> ſo much contends for; nor yet in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101330:17"/>Remiſſion of Sin neither, the neceſſity of which he would inferr in caſe the other be denyed; but in the imputation of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and obeying the Goſpel for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, to which Mr. <hi>S.</hi> ſaith, pardon is promiſed: And if ſo, then Mr. <hi>F.</hi> hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed us what he had a mind to do, but not at all performed what he undertook.</p>
            <p>But when Mr. <hi>F.</hi> aſſerts, That unleſs we are juſtified by the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs in his ſenſe of Imputation, we cannot be ſaid to be juſtified <hi>properly,</hi> but only to be <hi>pardoned,</hi> and that to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned is not to be <hi>juſtified properly:</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds therein upon a miſtaken ground, and confounds the terms and conditions of the original Law and Goſpel Covenant toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For he ſuppoſeth, that in order to our Juſtification in a <hi>proper</hi> ſenſe, we muſt one way or other have ſuch a Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as will anſwer the demands of the Law in point of perfect obedience, and of the Goſpel otherwiſe, and which will juſtifie us againſt all accuſations to the contrary. And that therefore we having no ſuch Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of our own, we cannot be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by having the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt made ours by Imputation, that we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101330:18"/>may therewith anſwer the demands and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations of the Law. Or in caſe we ſhould not be juſtified by the Imputation of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to anſwer the demands of the Law, yet that then we muſt be juſtified by being pardoned, and Pardon is not Juſtification properly ſo called.</p>
            <p>But while he argues at this rate, he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlooks what God hath done to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede and relax the rigorous terms of the primitive Law, by a new Law of Grace eſtabliſhed in Chriſt with all Mankind, and according to which he will now proceed with us, and not according to the rigorous demands of the primitive Law. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this, to wit, God's relaxing the old and introducing new terms of Juſtification and Life, it follows, that neither a perfect Legal Righteouſneſs is now neceſſary to Juſtification, nor yet that Juſtification muſt conſiſt only in pardon of Sin, though we have no ſuch Righteouſneſs inherent or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted (in Mr. <hi>F</hi>'s. ſenſe of Imputation) as will anſwer the demands of the Law in point of perfection.</p>
            <p>Such a Righteouſneſs is not now <hi>neceſſary</hi> to Juſtification. Firſt, becauſe that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101330:18"/>which once made it neceſſary to that end, is now relaxed by a new Law: this I have ſhewed before
<note n="*" place="margin">This new Law doth not relax the duty due by the old, hut alter the condition onwhich the divine favour was at firſt enjoyable, and hath now made ſincere obedience to it and to the Goſpel, the condition of it inſtead of ſinleſs perfection: And it grants pardon of all paſt offences againſt both, to ſuch as are justified againſt the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of not having performed the Condition, and of all after-offences alſo, that are conſiſtent with godly ſincerity: By reaſon whereof an anſwering the old demands of the Law, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection, is not now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to juſtification, neither as inherent in us, nor as impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, otherwiſe than as Christ's perfect righteouſneſs is imputed to us in the fruits and benefits of it, which is quite an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thing than the imputation of his righteouſneſs it ſelf to us; differing as much as the ects of his mediation differ from the benefits received thereby.</note>. Secondly, becauſe by this new Law the Righteouſneſs, which conſiſteth in a penetential rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating obedienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Faith, is made the condition upon which Pardon and Life are promiſed: And becauſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is by God counted to us for Righteouſneſs, like as a fulfilling of the Legal Condition would have been counted our Legal Righteouſneſs, had we never ſinned.</p>
            <p>Although the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt's Active and Paſſive Obedience, is that Righteouſneſs by which the Covenant it
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101330:19"/>ſelf, and the benefits of it, were conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally obtained for us, and granted to us: And although it is of God's mercy, and by vertue of Chriſt's Merits, and the Promiſe and Ordination of God, that we come to have any title to Pardon and Life, when we have performed the Condition, and not by vertue of any merit or deſert in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance it ſelf; yet this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt does not entitle us to Pardon and Life, until we have performed the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on our part required thereto, which is ſuch a believing as aforeſaid. And in the laſt iſſue we are accounted by God Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous or Unrighteous, according as we have, or have not perform'd the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>God's deſign towards us is to reſtore us to happineſs, and in order thereto to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and bring again into our Nature thoſe Vertues in which our likeneſs to God at firſt did conſiſt; by the loſs of which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came miſerable, and without a recovery of which we cannot be happy. And as moſt ſuitable to this deſign, God hath made ſuch a Faith the Condition of Pardon and Life, as by which the renovation of our Nature is gradually wrought, and without which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101330:19"/>we have no ground to expect thoſe benefits, how deſirable ſoever they are to us, and notwithſtanding all that Chriſt hath done and ſuffered to obtain them for us.</p>
            <p>To ſuppoſe that God accounts us Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and ſo confers a title to Pardon and Life, only by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed, without reſpect to our being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the Spirit of our minds, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by Faith, is to ſuppoſe him acting diſagreably to his own deſign and method of Grace in recovering us from our undone condition. To think we are made Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous only by what our Saviour hath done without us, without being renewed by a work of Faith within us: To ſuppoſe we are by the Imputation of Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs delivered from the danger of the Hell without us, without being at all freed from the Hell within us, which conſiſts in unnatural Luſts, and the uneaſie effects of them: To imagine that God ſhould reſtore us to a participation of the priviledges of his Children by the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, without reſtoring us at all to a participation in the Divine and New Nature of his Children, is abſurd, and that which is oppoſed by the conſtant tenour of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101330:20"/>Divine Doctrine in the holy Scriptures: And yet theſe are but the natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the Doctrine of being juſtified by the imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>alone,</hi> and of being juſtified by Faith <hi>alone</hi> as abſtracted from it's effect of renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us. And if either of theſe Doctrines were true, we might have an immediate ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to Pardon and Salvation without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and without being born again; unleſs we will ſuppoſe that Juſtification does not immediately entitle us to theſe; which to ſuppoſe is as abſurd as any of the reſt: For what, I pray you, would ſuch a Juſtification ſigniſie?</p>
            <p>And then as concerning the other thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That if we have not by the Imputation of Chriſt's perfect Righteouſneſs, a Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to anſwer the demands of the Law, that then, as Mr. <hi>F.</hi> infers, we can have no Juſtification but what conſiſts in the remiſſion of Sins; I anſwer: That for the ſame reaſon that we are accounted Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous upon our performing the Condition of the promiſe, pardon cannot be our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, but a benefit conſequent upon it.</p>
            <p>For if God's owning or avouching the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101330:20"/>Condition to be performed on our part (as he does when it is performed) on which he hath promiſed Pardon and Salvation, be his juſtifying of us, or his accounting us righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous according to the tenour of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, as indeed it is; then Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is not our Juſtification it ſelf, but one of the benefits unto which our Juſtification by vertue of the New Covenant doth entitle us: for the one is promiſed but on condition of the other. And as the thing promiſed, and the Condition on which it is promiſed, are not the ſame, ſo neither is the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or accounting us righteous, as having performed the Condition of the Promiſe of Pardon, and the actual Pardon it ſelf, the ſame; but ſo much as theſe differ, ſo much does Juſtification and Pardon differ.</p>
            <p>But yet for all that, I do not deny but that in a large ſenſe, as Juſtification is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Condemnation, it may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend remiſſion of Sins. That is, if by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation you underſtand both conviction of impenitency (which is the oppoſite to Juſtification properly) and the obligation or obnoxiouſneſs thereby to ſuffer the pains of the ſecond Death: And by Juſtification both a vindication from impenitency and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101330:21"/>unbelief (which is Juſtification properly) and alſo a diſcharge thereby from obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to eternal puniſhment, then, as I ſaid, Juſtification thus oppoſed to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation does indeed include in it remiſſion of Sin; though when ſtrictly and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly conſidered, Juſtification ſeems to be one thing, and Pardon of Sin another.</p>
            <p>It is wont to be alledged, That when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. that <hi>God imputeth Righteouſneſs without Works;</hi> the meaning is, That he imputeth the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt to us without any Works of ours at all, Legal or Evangelical, External or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal. And becauſe great ſtreſs is laid on it by ſome, I will briefly ſhew how the Context directs us to another ſenſe of thoſe words.</p>
            <p>The Scope of the Apoſtle in this and the former Chapter is to prove, that Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proceeds from God of <hi>Grace</hi> and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and not of <hi>Debt.</hi> To make this good, he ſhews here that it muſt needs be ſo, becauſe it is vouchſafed not unto ſuch who have been alwayes righteous (for he had proved before, Chap. 3. that there are none ſuch, but that all, both Jews and Gentiles have ſinned) but to ſuch as have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101330:21"/>been <hi>ungodly,</hi> when once they believe, and therefore ceaſe to be ſo, and become ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely righteous. And the Apoſtle's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon depends upon this manifeſt truth, That ſuch as have once ſinned can never by any after-works, which they can do, merit the Divine favour as a Debt due to them by deſert of their Works, nor are capable of that favour upon any other terms, than what God of his mere Grace is pleaſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point as the Condition of it, as he hath done that of Faith. <hi>For to him that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted to him for righteouſneſs,</hi> ver. 5.</p>
            <p>And to prove as well as to aſſert that God juſtifieth none upon account of their having been alwayes righteous, and in his favour (as ſome Jews fancied themſelves to have been upon account of their obſerving the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as he in the Goſpel who ſaid, <hi>All theſe have I kept from my youth up</hi>) he ſhew's out of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> how that the ancient godly Jews did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes eſteem their happineſs of being in God's favour, not to proceed from the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of their Works in obſerving the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but from the Grace and Mercy of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101330:22"/>God in forgiving their Sins, and accepting their ſincere endeavours to pleaſe him. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as David</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>deſcribes the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of the man to whom God. imputeth righteouſnes without works, ſaying, Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered,</hi> ver. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>And you may eaſily diſcern, if you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, that what is ſaid in this ſixth and ſeventh verſes, is to back and make good what he had ſaid in verſ. 5. touching God's juſtifying men upon their believing, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they had been in a ſtate of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs before: And to ſhew that if he juſtifie ſuch men upon ſuch terms; Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation muſt needs proceed of Grace, and not of Debt or merit of Works, of which he had ſpoken verſ. 4. ſaying, <hi>Now to him that worketh the reward is not reckoned of Grace, but of Debt.</hi> So that in making a Judgment of what Works St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, when he ſaith, <hi>Righteouſneſs is imputed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works,</hi> verſ. 6. if you do but take your riſe from what's ſaid in verſ. 4. touching ſuch Works, the reward of which is reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not of Grace, but of Debt, and ſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the diſcourſe and the deſign of it to verſ. 6. you will find that you cannot fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101330:22"/>turn aſide to another, but muſt needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him to this ſenſe, to wit, That the Righteouſneſs which is by Faith, of which he had ſpoken in verſ. 5. is imputed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch Works as make the reward to be not of Grace, but of Debt, mentioned v. 4. His Argument runs thus in other words: They, to whom God imputed Righteouſneſs heretofore, were ſuch as ſtood in need of forgiveneſs from God; therefore they could not poſſibly merit his favour.</p>
            <p>And although St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not improve the words of the Pſalmiſt further than to prove that no man is reſtored to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine favour and the bleſſedneſs conſequent upon it, without forgiveneſs of Sins, and that therefore it muſt needs be of Grace, and not of Debt and Merit that any man attains it by being juſtified, this being his end in alledging them: Yet it's alſo evident by the words immediately following thoſe the Apoſtle here recites, That <hi>Godly ſincerity</hi> is the conditional qualification required of ſuch to whom the favour of forgiveneſs is vouchſafed: For it's there ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord imputeth not iniquity, and in whoſe Spirit there is no guile:</hi> No guile notes the <hi>Sincerity</hi> I ſpeak
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101330:23"/>of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.2. And it's to the ſame ſenſe, when in the writings of the New Teſtament Faith, as the <hi>Principle</hi> of Sincerity and of the Divine Nature and Life, is made the Condition of Pardon.</p>
            <p>And now if what hath been ſaid amounts to any fair account of the Apoſtle's ſcope and deſign in thoſe forementioned verſes, and of the ſenſe of the ſeveral Phraſes by which it is expreſt (and I leave you to judg whether it doth or no) then I can ſee no reaſon, why by Righteouſneſs imputed without Works we ſhould underſtand the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, but rather the Righteouſneſs of Faith properly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; which Faith the Apoſtle there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirms to be imputed for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but doth not ſo much as mention Chriſt in thoſe verſes, much leſs the imputation of his Righteouſneſs unto Juſtification, as excluſive of all manner of Works. It is not the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, but Grace and Faith, that are in this contexture of Scripture oppoſed to Works: Nor are Works oppoſed to Faith neither, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>Merit,</hi> as they make the reward to be of Debt, and not of Grace. And when I ſay this, I do for all that with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101330:23"/>all thankfulneſs acknowledge and profeſs, That the Righteouſneſs or Obedience of Chriſt's Life and Death doth with a high hand operate to our Juſtification, and ſo as neither our Faith nor any thing in us, or done by us, can do, but in a way altogether tranſcending it, though not in Mr. <hi>F</hi>'s. way of Imputation; nor is it in this Scripture ſet forth as it is in others.</p>
            <p>It's true indeed, the Righteouſneſs the Apoſtle treats of in this place is ſtiled Righteouſneſs <hi>imputed:</hi> But the reaſon is not, becauſe it is not inherent in the perſons themſelves to whom it is imputed, but in Chriſt, and made theirs only by imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for it is the Faith of the Perſon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that is here ſaid to be counted or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him for Righteouſneſs. And the reaſon, why it is called a Righteouſneſs <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted,</hi> may be, becauſe it is not naturally, and of it ſelf, or in its own nature a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs that would juſtifie a man, as <hi>Adam</hi>'s was before his fall, but it is only by Divine <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> Grace and Favour that it is ſo; <hi>God juſtifies us freely by his Grace,</hi> Rom. 3.24. <hi>It is of Faith, that it might be by Grace,</hi> as it follows, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. As it is by the Juſtification or Ordinance of a King
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101330:24"/>that ſuch a piece of Coin paſſeth currant for ſo much, whether it be of the intrinſick value or no, even ſo by vertue of God's inſtitution, and for Chriſt's ſake, Faith is made to paſs for, and to be reckoned and accounted to us for Righteouſneſs, and to entitle us to thoſe benefits, which in its own Nature it doth not merit. If it were a perfect Righteouſneſs in its own Nature, as <hi>Adam</hi>'s was, it would need no Pardon to accompany it, as it does, and would ſecure us as well from temporal as eternal death, which yet it doth not: But it being a Righteouſneſs by Inſtitution and Grace; how far it ſhall be beneficial to us, and to what ends and purpoſes it ſhall ſerve, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend wholly upon the good will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, and are knowable only ſo far to us, as he hath been pleaſed to put them into promiſe, by vertue of which promiſe made upon condition of ſuch Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not by merit of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf, we come to have a title to the promiſed benefits, ſuch as are remiſſion of Sin and eternal Life.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>F.</hi> cannot underſtand, but that <hi>it is repugnant to the immutability and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Holineſs of God to juſtifie us upon an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101330:24"/>obedience, the Law commanding that which is perfect, and thinks for him to do ſo would be to pronounce an unjuſt perſon juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he ſhould conſider, That God in juſtifying us doth not pronounce us juſt, as not having ſinned (for that's impoſſible for him indeed to do) but as having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Condition, on which he in his Goſpel-Covenant hath promiſed to pardon our Sin. And in doing this he doth not prouounce unjuſt perſons juſt; for they are juſt with an Evangelical Righteouſneſs, juſt in the Goſpel ſenſe, and ſo ſtiled from place to place in the Scripture, as I have ſhew'd. And although the Evangelical Righteouſneſs and Obedience, upon which God is pleaſed to juſtifie us, be imperfect, if meaſured by the Law, yet it is perfect as to its end appointed by God, when mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the Goſpel, by which we are to be tryed whether we be righteous or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous: And whoſoever (being <hi>adult</hi>) is <hi>not righteous</hi> in this ſenſe, <hi>ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 69. but thoſe that are thus <hi>righteous ſhall go into life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> Matth. 25.46.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing Evangelical Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Obedience to be <hi>Comparatively</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101330:25"/>whether compared with what man in innocency had, and was capable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; or whether compared with a gradual perfection of Righteouſneſs and Obedience of the ſame kind; and ſuppoſing it to be only ſincere obedience according to the preſent circumſtances a man is in: Let us weigh and conſider whether or no it be not conſiſtent with the Holineſs of God to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie men upon ſuch Righteouſneſs and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience when found in them, when withal we take in what hath been done by Chriſt the Mediatour to make way for it. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Mr. <hi>F.</hi> doth not ſuppoſe, that God by the Holineſs of his Nature is naturally and neceſſarily reſtrained from ſhewing favour to men, after once they have been guilty of Sin, and have made themſelves obnoxious to the effects of his high diſpleaſure; for if he were, we were all ſtill in an ill caſe, and there would be then no ſuch thing as <hi>Grace</hi> extant in the World, which yet is ſo illuſtrious and glorious, as that it is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubject matter of the Goſpel. Grace and mercy are as eſſentially in God as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: And therefore we muſt take heed of framing ſuch notions of his Holineſs as to leave no place for the exerciſe of his Grace
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101330:25"/>and Mercy. God no doubt is at liberty to recede from his own right, as well as men are, in remitting debts and pardoning offences to what degree, and upon what terms he pleaſeth, only he, as <hi>Rector</hi> of the World, hath reſpect therein unto good order and government.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing all this, we muſt ſuppoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that ſuch acts of Grace and Favour towards offending Sinners, as do not in the leaſt encourage them to continue in Sin, nor any other Creature in the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is innocent to fall into a ſtate of like Rebellion as man hath done, but are of a quite contrary tendency, will very well conſiſt with the end of his Government, as he is <hi>Rector</hi> of the World, and with the Righteouſneſs and Juſtice of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf. Now the reaſon and end of executing Juſtice upon Delinquents is either to recover them themſelves to good order and behaviour, or to deterr others from falling into like Rebellion againſt God: For otherwiſe God <hi>delighteth not in the death</hi> (as ſuch) <hi>of him that dies,</hi> Ezek. 18. Provided then that theſe ends of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment be ſecured in ſhewing favour, the ſtighteouſneſs and Juſtice of God will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101330:26"/>ſuffer any diſparagement, how great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Grace and Favour be that is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Offenders. But now that God in juſtifying men upon account of <hi>ſincere</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and <hi>inherent</hi> righteouſneſs, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what hath been done by our Lord Chriſt to make way for it, and to bring things to that iſſue, does not in the leaſt countenance Sin paſt, or encourage to the committing of it for time to come, but that which is altogether contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto will ſufficiently appear, if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That notwithſtanding God is ſo good and gracious, ſo merciful and ready to forgive as he is, yet he would not grant any terms at all of receiving us into favour again, having once ſinned, except his own dear Son himſelf would take upon him our Nature, and become a Sacrifice, to make an Atonement for our Sin; nor ſpare him when he had undertaken ſo to be, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that great love wherewith he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, but delivered him up to death for us all, when he undertook to become a propitiation for our Sins, rather than we ſhould have no terms of pardon granted. God's granting terms of pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101330:26"/>to his favour upon no cheaper terms, did clearly demonſtrate him to be an enemy and hater of Sin in the higheſt, and ſo irreconcilable to it, as that no Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner could have any ground to hope to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the puniſhment due to it, but upon obſerving that Condition of eſcaping it, the obtaining of which coſt ſo dear. In that Chriſt thus ſuffered in the fleſh, he <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Sin in the fleſh</hi> (as the phraſe is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.) and that effectually, and with a witneſs. Hereby he condemned it in the ſight of Heaven and Earth, yea, and of Hell too, as a thing moſt abominable to God, and contrary to his Nature, and to the goodneſs and equity of his Laws and Government, when deliverance from the deſert of it could be obtained at no cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate or eaſier terms, than the Son of God his ſuffering in the Sinners ſtead; no not upon repentance it ſelf without this. In that God hath thus <hi>ſet forth his Son to be a propitiation for Sin through Faith in his Blood, it is to declare his Righteouſneſs in the remiſſion of Sins that are paſt</hi> (that he is righteous although he forgive) <hi>and that he might be juſt</hi> even when he is <hi>the juſtifier of him that believeth in Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 3.25, 26.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101330:27"/>
            <p>Secondly, When God for Chriſt's ſake, and for what he hath done and ſuffered, did grant terms of Grace, by which we Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners might come to be juſtified, pardoned, and ſaved; yet they were ſuch, and none other, but what tend to <hi>reclaim</hi> us from Sin and Rebellion, and to <hi>reduce</hi> us to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and of Rebels to make us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good Subjects. And in doing this, God is far from countenancing Sin, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing diſagreeable to the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wiſdom, and goodneſs of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; indeed ſo far from it, that it highly commends and ſets theſe off.</p>
            <p>The terms of favour granted for Chriſt's ſake are ſuch as theſe; That believing and being perſwaded in our own minds that God is good, and ready to forgive for his Son's ſake, we heartily repent that ever we rebell'd againſt him, and that we deſiſt from continuing in our Rebellion any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and that we return to our duty, and <hi>ſincerely endeavour</hi> to pleaſe him in all things for the future. It's true indeed, God knows, that by reaſon of the wounds and diſeaſe we got by our fall, and while we were in rebellion, we have brought ſo great debility upon our ſelves, as that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101330:27"/>though we do return to him, yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do him ſuch ſervice now, as man was capable of performing before the fall, and his running into rebellion; and therefore he is content for his Son's ſake, to accept of ſuch ſervice, as we in this ſtate of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and frailty are capable of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, provided we do the beſt we well can, and make uſe of all helps and means afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, whereby we may gather ſtrength, and grow better, and do better; and are heartily ſorry that ever we have made our ſelves ſo uncapable, as we have done, of doing him better ſervice. Theſe and ſuch like are the terms granted us for Chriſt's ſake.</p>
            <p>But without ſome ſuch Change as this God hath not promiſed to receive any man into favour. Now then, if it be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the righteouſneſs and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Government, for God to offer and promiſe to receive Sinners into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour again upon theſe terms and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (and I cannot think Mr. <hi>F.</hi> will ſay it is:) Then it cannot be inconſiſtent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with for him to <hi>own</hi> that they have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed theſe conditions, when indeed they have, and ſo to own them now for his true
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101330:28"/>and faithful Servants and Subjects to their power, and according to the term ſet in his act of Grace, which is his juſtifying of them, or the imputing to them for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſuch their faithful ſervice as they are capable of performing.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, I dare appeal to Mr. <hi>F's.</hi> better and more impartial Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether it be not conſiſtent with the Holineſs of God to juſtifie men upon the terms aforeſaid. I confeſs I cannot poſſibly underſtand, why it ſhould not as well conſiſt with the Holineſs of God to juſtifie us upon our believing, and upon our obeying the Goſpel too, as it is to do it upon our believing alone: And Mr. <hi>F.</hi> does not think that God doth juſtifie us at all, or impute righteouſneſs to us at all in one ſenſe or another, without our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. So that the imputation of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to us for our juſtification, in which ſenſe ſoever we take it, depends upon our own act in believing, and ſo likewiſe is the application of what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for our juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuſpended upon our believing. In what Notion ſoever you underſtand the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt's
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101330:28"/>life and ſatisfaction of his death to be made; as whether by being imputed to us in it ſelf, or vertually by having our Faith for the ſake thereof imputed to us for Righteouſneſs; yet ſtill this applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depends upon our believing, becauſe God hath made that the condition of it, without which Chriſt ſhall profit us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>I take notice further, how Mr. <hi>F.</hi> by his Notion of having the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us otherwiſe than in its effects, is led to think and ſay that our Sins alſo were otherwiſe imputed to Chriſt than in the effects of them. <hi>To ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that our Sins were imputed to Chriſt in the effects of them, but not in the guilt, is to contradict all principles of Reaſon: For guilt and obnoxiouſneſs to puniſhment being equipollent phraſes, he cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be made liable to the laſt upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our Sins, without having been brought under the firſt;</hi> p. 410.</p>
            <p>Nor is it imaginable, let me ſay, how any perſon ſhould come under the <hi>guilt</hi> of Sin, that hath not been acceſſary to the <hi>fault:</hi> For guilt implyes two things; a fault committed by him that is guilty of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101330:29"/>it, and the being under an obligation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſuffer the puniſhment due to it, and this obligation of a guilty perſon to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer proceeds from the demerit of his fault or crime. And will Mr. <hi>F.</hi> ſay that Chriſt was guilty of our Sins by being in the fault? Or that he came under an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſuffer by being in the fault, and from the demerit of the fault? God ſorbid. Chriſt was no otherwiſe obliged to ſuffer for our Sins, than by his own voluntary conſent in concurrence with the will of God his Father, in offering himſelf as a Sacrifice to make an Atonement by his own Blood. And after this manner indeed by being a Sacrifice the Beaſts in time of the Law, that were offered in Sacrifice for Sin, did bear the Sins of thoſe for whom they were offered. But I ſhould think he were little better than a Beaſt in his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſhould ſay thoſe Beaſts were guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Sins of thoſe, for whom they were offered in Sacriſice.</p>
            <p>But it's true, as one truth leads to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo it's too commonly ſeen, men are tempted to commit one errour to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defend another, which I think is the Caſe now before us. Otherwiſe Mr. <hi>F.</hi> would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101330:29"/>have ventured to ſay Chriſt was brought under the guilt of our Sins, and had the guilt of them derived upon him, but only the better, as he thought no doubt, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate his Notion of our being in the Innocency and Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, by having it imputed to us, and derived upon us.</p>
            <p>But this is not the only inconvenience that attends this Notion of having the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt it ſelf imputed to us for our juſtification, and not only in its happy effects; for it ſeems to me to oppoſe the doctrine of forgiveneſs of Sin: Nay, I pray you conſider, whether it doth not evacuate it, and leave no place for ſuch a thing. For if we, in Mr. <hi>F's. Law ſenſe,</hi> have by Chriſt paid all the Debt the Law could any wayes demand of us, both in point of obedience and of ſuffering for our diſobedience, by having his obedience and ſufferings themſelves imputed to us, and not only in the beneficial effects of them: How then, I pray you, can we be ſaid to be forgiven by God, to whom the Debt thus paid was due? Does that man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give a Debt to me which I have paid him by another, though not by my ſelf? A Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101330:30"/>Diſcharge I may have in ſuch a caſe from the Creditour, but no man will ſay he hath for given me my Debt.</p>
            <p>I think it will beſt become us to ſay, as the Scripture doth, <hi>That God for Chriſt's ſake hath forgiven us;</hi> and not to ſay we have paid him what in the rigour of Juſtice he could demand of us, if not more, to wit, perfect obedience and ſuffering too, which the Law in its utmoſt rigour never demanded nor required. We may well and thankfully take up with this, That God, in conſideration of what Chriſt hath become, done, and ſuffered for our ſakes, for our benefit, hath paſt an Act of Oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to remember our Sins and Iniquities no more, provided, and on condition that we repent of our rebellion againſt God, and return to our Loyalty and Duty in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him truly, ſincerely, and heartily, as every one doth that ſo believes, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to become capable of being juſtified, pardoned and ſaved.</p>
            <p>Furthermore conſider I pray you, That if Chriſt's fulfilling of the Law be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, as that we are looked upon as having fulfilled it in him, how could it then be neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould dye
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101330:30"/>for our Sins? If we by the imputation of Chriſt's fulfilling the Law have paid the whole debt of Obedience which was ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, we ſhould then owe no debt of Suffering for the breach of it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Chriſt would not have needed by ſuffering to have paid any ſuch Debt for us, no more than for himſelf, who had no Sin to ſuffer for.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider yet further, That if Chriſt hath paid our whole debt of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Law by fulfilling it for us, and then imputing it to us, is there not by this Notion, if admitted, a way paved and prepared for Libertines, to think that then they need not pay it too? to think that God is no ſuch auſteer Creditour as to exact the ſame debt twice; firſt of the Surery, and then of the Principal too? And let me tell you this, Sir, that I have very great reaſon from my obſervation for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, to be confident, that it was from this Opinion, which Mr. <hi>F.</hi> now defends, touching the Imputation of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to us otherwiſe than in its bleſſed effects, that Antinomianiſm took its firſt riſe among us in this Nation, and Ranteriſm alſo out of that. For how elſe could it
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101330:31"/>be poſſible that men ſhould fancy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pure and perfect, and free from all Sin in the midſt of thoſe abominations ſome of them gave themſelves up to, but only that they thought themſelves to be ſo by having another's righteouſneſs impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, ſo as they to become for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally righteous by it, as he himſelf was, ſave only in the point of imputation. I muſt confeſs I cannot think that any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that is of the Goſpel indeed, which is a Doctrine <hi>according to Godlineſs</hi> in the whole and every part of it, can be ſo lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as this is, to natural inferences tending to ungodlineſs, or to weaken that which is in the Doctrine of Juſtification rightly underſtood againſt Ungodlineſs.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, when the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the great benefits of remiſſion of Sin and eternal Life, is ſuſpended upon our being righteous by a righteouſneſs inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in us, ſuch as conſiſts in Repentance, Faith, &amp;c. this becomes the greateſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Godlineſs imaginable, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports directly with that which is God's great deſign by the Goſpel, which is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover man again to Happineſs by Holineſs, from which he firſt fell by tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:101330:31"/>
            <p>But that you may have down weight in this Argument, and more if more can be, I will offer one thing more to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which perhaps may deſerve it, and that is, Whether thoſe that deny the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Grace of Faith and Sanctification by Faith to be imputed for Righteouſneſs in Juſtification, (as they uſually do, who hold that Chriſt's Righteouſneſs it ſelf is ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted) do not thereby make themſelves guilty in ſome reſpect, and to a degree, of the pernicious errour of the falſe Apoſtles and Judaiſing Chriſtians, for which in the groſs they were charged with <hi>falling from Grace,</hi> with making <hi>Chriſt to become of none effect to them,</hi> and with <hi>perverting the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt.</hi> For I think I ſhall make it evident that their errour lay in two things, (unleſs you will add thereto their opinion of meriting) the one in denying the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Internal Righteouſneſs unto Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; the other, in holding an external one in conjunction with Faith in Chriſt to be ſufficient to that end.</p>
            <p>Now whether Mr. <hi>F.</hi> himſelf doth deny inherent Grace to be <hi>at all</hi> imputed for Righteouſneſs in our Juſtification, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that it <hi>only</hi> is ſo, I confeſs I cannot
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101330:32"/>ſay: But certain it is, that he denies it to be ſufficient without the imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs in the ſenſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation wherein he is oppoſed. One while he grants that <hi>in reference to the mere demands of the Goſpel, we may in a proper ſenſe be ſaid to be juſtified;</hi> p. 416. At another turn he ſaith, <hi>that, ſecluding not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the righteouſneſs of Chriſt's life, but the ſatisfaction of his death, as the matter, and the imputation of it as the formal Cauſe of Juſtification, it ſeems repugnant unto the immutability and eſſential Holineſs of God to juſtifie us upon an imperfect obedience</hi> (ſuch as he accounts Evangelical obedience to be) <hi>the Law which requireth a perfect remaining ſtill in force, and denouncing wrath in caſe of every failure.</hi> By which he ſeems to hold (how conſiſtently with what I before recited, do you judge) that it is inconſiſtent with the Holineſs of God to juſtifie us upon an Evangelical Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, becauſe imperfect.</p>
            <p>But whether Mr. <hi>F.</hi> joyns the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of inherent Grace together in the buſineſs of Juſtification, or whether he wholly denies the imputation of the latter,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101330:32"/>and affirms only the imputation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, I ſhall not further enquire. But it's well known that thoſe who are wont to plead the ſame cauſe with Mr. <hi>F.</hi> touching the neceſſity of the imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs unto Juſtification, and in that ſenſe wherein he is oppoſed, are wont alſo to exclude inherent Grace, as being neither imputed for Righteouſneſs in Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, nor as neceſſary thereunto ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedently. Mr. <hi>E. Polhill</hi> (a Gentleman doubtleſs of a good Spirit) another of Mr. <hi>S's.</hi> Antagoniſts, in his anſwer to him ſaith in p. 75. <hi>In Juſtification no other Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs can take place, but the active and paſſive one of Chriſt, which anſwers the pure and righteous Law in every thing.</hi> And in p. 321. he ſaith, <hi>Obedience to God's commands is indeed the way to Heaven, but its no where made an ingredient into our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi> And p. 365. ſpeaking of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. ſaith, that <hi>the Apoſtle in this place doth not only exclude external Phariſaical righteouſneſs, but even inherent Graces in the matter of Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the common opinion of thoſe that have gone that way hath been, That San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification is ſubſequent to Juſtification,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101330:33"/>and not ſo much as in order of Nature go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before it, or to be any ingredient in it, and conſequently not <hi>eſſentially neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to it. Now then, that which I ſay is this; that if I can make it appear, that the denying the neceſſity of internal righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto Juſtification was one part of the grievous errour of the Judaiſing Chriſtians, it will be enough to ſpoil the reputation of the ſame opinion, though found in better men than they were: And whether I ſhall not make it evidently to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo to be, I ſhall leave you to judge, after you have weighed what I ſhall now lay before you.</p>
            <p>Their Crime was, I conceive, a partial revolt or turning unto the worſt of Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, ſaving their retaining a profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt; to think that an external righteouſneſs without an internal, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to juſtification and ſalvation. The unbelieving Jews, to whom they turned in part, were quite degenerated from their worthy Anceſtors, and all that remained faithful among them, who all held the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Grace of Love to God, fear of him, uprightneſs of heart towards him, truth in the inward parts, neceſſary to intereſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101330:33"/>them in his favour, and the bleſſing of the everlaſting Covenant.</p>
            <p>But the degenerate Jews thought an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Righteouſneſs, ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> had while a Phariſee, and ſuch as would juſtifie them in the ſight of men, according to the terms of the political Covenant, by which they were externally governed by God as they were his Commonwealth, would juſtifie them as to their eternal eſtate. Of which grand miſtake our Saviour (<hi>Matth.</hi> 5.) laboured to convince them, by ſhewing that no leſs was required by God in order to that, than an <hi>inward purity,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided them with their making clean the <hi>outſide</hi> of the Cup and Platter, when <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> they were full of extortion and exceſs, of ravening and wickedneſs; with their appearing <hi>outwardly</hi> Righteous unto men, when <hi>within</hi> they were full of Hypocriſie and iniquity, and told his hearers that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their Righteouſneſs exceeded theirs, they ſhould never enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: that except they were born again they could not ſee the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it was to this monſtrouſly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt part of Judaiſm to which the Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtians did revolt, or turn rather
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:101330:34"/>(for many of them were Gentiles,) becauſe without this, their errour in adhering to the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> as neceſſary to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, would not have been ſo damnable as the Scripture repreſents it to be, calling it a <hi>perverting the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> a being <hi>removed to another Goſpel,</hi> a <hi>falling from Grace, a making of Chriſt to become of none effect to them, (Gal.</hi> 1.7. and 5.2, 4.) which it would not have been, if there had been nothing elſe in it than a perſwaſion that they were under an obligation of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as well as the Law of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For there were many thouſands of the Jews which believed, who were yet zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and thought themſelves ſtill under the obligation of it, (<hi>Acts</hi> 21.) who yet could never be ſaid upon that account to be fallen from Grace, or to be removed from the Goſpel of Chriſt to another Goſpel, ſo long as they were <hi>really</hi> for an <hi>internal</hi> Righteouſneſs as <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> to Juſtification and Salvation, as well as an external. For all the faithful Jews under the Law, before the Law and after the Law, yea and all the Gentiles too, that had this internal Righteouſneſs, as well as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101330:34"/>an external, were all juſtified through the Grace of God exhibited in the univerſal Covenant made in Chriſt, and granted for his ſake, whether they had any explicite or diſtinct knowledge of that Covenant, or not, or of Chriſt in whom it was confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>In every Nation he that feareth God and worketh Righteouſneſs is accepted of him: and if the Uncircumciſion did but keep the righteouſneſs of the Law, the internal</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs deſigned by it, <hi>their Uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was counted for Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When on the other hand <hi>he was not a Jew</hi> at any time (in the ſenſe there ſpoken of) <hi>who was one outwardly in the fleſh</hi> only, <hi>but he was a Jew which was ſo inwardly, and Circumciſion was that of the heart in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of the Law, <hi>and not in the Letter only, whoſe praiſe</hi> or approbation <hi>was from God,</hi> whether it were from men or no, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have become as a Jew to the Jews to gain the Jews, as he did in obſerving Jewiſh Rites (<hi>Acts</hi> 21.) and in circumciſing <hi>Timothy:</hi> nor have ſaid as he did, that <hi>God had received</hi> ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Jews, who yet made Conſcience of Jewiſh difference and diſtinction <hi>of meats
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101330:35"/>and dayes (Rom.</hi> 14.) if a mere perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of being under the obligation of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> had been ſo dangerous and damnable, as he affirms the errour of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſing Chriſtians to be.</p>
            <p>The very nature of the oppoſition, which the Apoſtles made againſt the errour of the Judaiſing Chriſtians in their Epiſtles to the Churches among whom they were, ſufficiently diſcovers to us the nature of their errour to be the placing Juſtification in an <hi>external</hi> Righteouſneſs, and not in an <hi>internal.</hi> When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, if they were Circumciſed Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing, and that they were fallen from Grace that would be juſtified by the Law, and that the true Chriſtians <hi>waited for the hope of the Righteouſneſs which is by Faith,</hi> or which Faith produceth; he gives this reaſon of all, ſaying; <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion, but Faith which worketh by Love, i. e.</hi> by cauſing Love to God and Men, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. And again, <hi>for in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus neither Circumciſion availeth any thing, nor Uncircumciſion, but a new Creature,</hi> Gal. 6.15. And <hi>if any man be in Chriſt, he's a new Creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:101330:35"/>
            <p>And the Goſpel is declared by St <hi>Paul</hi> to be <hi>the miniſtration of Righteouſneſs, not in the Letter</hi> of the Law, <hi>but in the Spirit</hi> or internal Righteouſneſs which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Law, and more plainly and expreſly in the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. and that Chriſtians muſt <hi>ſerve in newneſs of Spirit, and not in the oldneſs of the Letter.</hi> And the benefits of the new Covenant of having God to be our God, and our Sins pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, belong only to them who have his <hi>Laws put in their mind, and written in their heart, Heb.</hi> 8. And that thoſe, <hi>who are born after the Spirit</hi> by regeneration, <hi>are Children ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe</hi> or tenour of the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, when as thoſe, who were <hi>born after the fleſh,</hi> and adhering only to the Letter of the Law for an external Righteouſneſs, were <hi>Children of the fleſh,</hi> or Legal Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Covenant: And this is ſet forth in an Allegory touching the two Covenants, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>All this ſerves not only to let us ſee the <hi>nature</hi> of that Righteouſneſs, by which the Judaiſing Chriſtians could not be juſtified as they <hi>expected,</hi> but alſo by way of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to that, truly and plainly to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to us the nature of that Evangelical Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101330:36"/>by which (in ſubordination to Chriſt's Righteouſneſs) we muſt be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if ever juſtified; both which doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs were the true deſign of the Scriptures I have brought together, that you uright ſee the harmony and concurrent teſtimony of the Scriptures in this matter.</p>
            <p>By this time I preſume you perceive, that the difference between the two ſorts of Judaiſing Chriſtians, the better and the worſe, lay much in this one point, to wit, that the one did, and the other did not hold <hi>internal</hi> Righteouſneſs neceſſary to Juſtification: For, excepting in this, they ſeem both to have been of one mind, both in profeſſing Faith in Chriſt, and in holding themſelves under the obligation of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> for Circumciſion and other Legal Rites. Now then, if that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing made ſo great a difference between them, as I have ſhew'd, what ſhall we then think of that opinion, by which ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter men among us than the corrupt Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtians were do thus far agree and fall in with them, as they do in denying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Righteouſneſs of inherent Grace to be neceſſary to our Juſtification, or that it doth enter it, or is any ingredient in it,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101330:36"/>but think it perfectly ſubſequent to it, not ſo much as admitting it to take place, or to come into being, until we are firſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified; nor ſo much as admitting that Faith in it ſelf is imputed for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but only the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt as apprehended by Faith: I ſay, what ſhall we think of this? Can we poſſibly think the ſame opinion to be a grievous errour in the Judaiſing Chriſtians, and yet to be Orthodox and Innocent in others?</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs where this opinion is as pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically held as it was by the corrupter ſort of the Judaiſing Chriſtians, it is as criminal and dangerous as it was in them; but ſo it is not, I confeſs, where it is held only ſpeculatively, as I ſuppoſe it to be by all thoſe of that perſwaſion that are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate and truly good. For they hold Regeneration and the inherent Grace of Sanctification neceſſary to Salvation, though not to Juſtification; and in holding this they practically hold it neceſſary to Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, even then while in ſpeculation and opinion they hold no abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of it in order thereto. For the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing upon this better principle, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Regeneration and Sanctification ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101330:37"/>to Salvation, and becoming Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, Sanctified, and internally Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thereupon, they come thereby to have this Evangelical Righteouſneſs imputed to them for ſuch as it is, that is for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; for ſo it is in the eye, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenour of the Evangelical Law; which Imputation is their Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This God does, although they do not know and believe all this, but think they were juſtified before they were ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied (which by interpretation is to think they were accounted righteous before they were ſo) that they were accounted righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Righteouſneſs of another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were at all righteous in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But God proceeds in juſtifying men, not according to by-opinions in men, while conſiſtent with real Holineſs, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what they are indeed and in truth in the <hi>temper</hi> of their hearts, and <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of their lives.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid thus much to eaſe thoſe of the opinion I oppoſe, as much as I can. For by reaſon that it is counter-ballanced by better principles in many, it is not ſo dangerous in them as it was in the corrupt Judaiſing Chriſtians. It was in them indeed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101330:37"/>mortiſerous and damnable if practiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perſiſted in, becauſe there was in them no ſuch thing to counter-ballance it in its operation, as a perſwaſion of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of internal Righteouſneſs unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, no more than unto Juſtification, as there is in theſe.</p>
            <p>And in this very reſpect, and their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of merit, doubtleſs it was, that the promoters of this grand errour were charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with perverting the Goſpel of Chriſt, and thoſe that practically adhered to them therein, with falling from Grace, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving themſelves of the benefit of Chriſt's death. And the reaſon of this is plain; becauſe the Grace of God in the Goſpel is <hi>limited</hi> and reſtrained in the <hi>laſt iſſue</hi> and <hi>event</hi> unto mens becoming <hi>Regenerate</hi> and internally righteous, as the <hi>condition with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which</hi> they ſhall neither be <hi>juſtified,</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, nor ſaved by the <hi>death</hi> of Chriſt, or <hi>any thing</hi> he hath done for the Salvation of Sinners. And therefore thoſe falſe Teachers, that taught Juſtification and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation attainable by Chriſt without ſuch internal Righteouſneſs, might well be charged with perverting the Goſpel of Chriſt, and thoſe Chriſtians with falling
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101330:38"/>from Grace, who cloſed with them in that opinion: For therein they departed and fell off from the true Notion and Idea of the Grace of the Goſpel, and the terms on which all the ſaving benefits are in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel promiſed by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now although this opinion of the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſity of the inherent Grace of Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Juſtification is check't and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled in its operation in thoſe that are full of the ſenſe of the neceſſity of it unto Salvation; yet by what hath been now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented it ſeems in it ſelf, and <hi>abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> from the <hi>better</hi> principle I have mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be the <hi>firſt ſtep</hi> towards falling from Grace in the ſenſe before explained, and is of dangerous conſequence, when it takes place in men who have no ſuch <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the neceſſity of internal Sanctification unto Salvation. For in ſuch caſe, Libertines and Carnal men will be apt to bear up them ſelves in hope (as is much to be feared they too frequently do) that if their believing <hi>only,</hi> abſtracted from its effects in renewing men, be <hi>ſufficient</hi> to <hi>procure</hi> the Imputation of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to them for their Juſtification in the fight of God, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of it <hi>ſelf</hi> to obtain it, that then it will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101330:38"/>be ſufficient alſo to <hi>ſave</hi> them, in as much as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>whom God juſtifieth, them he alſo glorifieth,</hi> and ſtileth the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of men, <hi>Juſtification unto life,</hi> and <hi>if God juſtifie, who is he that condemneth?</hi> And in this very reſpect, it is much to be ſeared, that this opinion too frequently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſnare of Death, and a ſtumbling ſtone to many, to content themſelves with that which is but a dead Faith, and ſome external form of Devotion and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without the internal, in mortifying all inordinate affection, and in governing their thoughts and paſſions; and to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſafe and in a good condition upon account of that, to the betraying of their Souls to deſtruction. And whether it may not be pronounced concerning all thoſe who expect Juſtification and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon account of their believing and hoping in Chriſt, and of an external Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs without an internal, that they are fallen from Grace, and that Chriſt ſhall profit them nothing, as well as it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the corrupt Judaiſing Chriſtians, is a queſtion I think you will eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:101330:39"/>
            <p>When we ſee then how fatal it was to the unbelieving Jews and Judaiſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to <hi>miſtake</hi> the <hi>tenour</hi> of God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the <hi>nature</hi> of the Covenant-Righteouſneſs, and to introduce a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <hi>another kind</hi> into the <hi>place and office</hi> of the <hi>internal Righteouſneſs</hi> which is by Faith, it may well make wary men cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, how they entertain any opinion that is in any degree like unto it.</p>
            <p>It hath been a <hi>miſtake</hi> of the Scriptures about the <hi>nature and kind</hi> of the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal-Covenant-Righteouſneſs, that hath <hi>occaſioned</hi> our Diſputes about it in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, as well as it did among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Apoſtles times, though the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference hath not been altogether ſo great, nor perhaps ſo dangerous now as it was then. And if it may not be burthenſome to you, I will very briefly give you yet ſome farther account of my thoughts and apprehenſions of the nature of this Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and of the ſenſe and meaning of ſome of thoſe Scriptures that treat of it, and have been miſtaken on the one ſide, or on the other.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:101330:39"/>
            <p>The tenour of God's Grace in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is to exhibit, declare, and ſhew, that ſince man by his fall hath made the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of felicity, and the avoiding of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, by perfect ſinleſs obedience, impra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable, that yet God will for Chriſt's ſake, as having undertaken for us, receive him into favour again upon condition that he do but heartily deſire, reſolve, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely endeavour for the future to become obedient, and to pleaſe him in all things ſo far as he is able with the helps and aſſiſtances internal and external, which God will vouchſafe, and heartily repent that ever he did otherwiſe; and that upon the ſame condition he will pardon all paſt ſins and future failings alſo, ſo far as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with ſincerity of Love and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This is ſummarily the glad tidings which by the Goſpel is publiſhed to the World.</p>
            <p>And a practical belief of this glad Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings is that which God accounts unto men for Righteouſneſs, as being the New-Covenant-Righteouſneſs. And that's a practical belief of it, when men ſo believe it as to practiſe according to it, in repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſincerely obeying, in hope of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101330:40"/>promiſed benefits. And this <hi>godly ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is the Righteouſneſs of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or Goſpel, as diſtinguiſhed from the Righteouſneſs which is of the Law, either as that imports perfect ſinleſs obedience, or elſe only an external Phariſaical Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>The Evangelical Righteouſneſs afore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, is in the New Teſtament ſometimes ſtiled the Righteouſneſs of <hi>God,</hi> as oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the unbelieving Jews and corrupt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſing Chriſtians <hi>own</hi> external Phariſaical Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. And this is called their <hi>own</hi> Righteouſneſs, as being only of their <hi>own chuſing,</hi> and not of God's appointing, as the condition on which they <hi>promiſed themſelves</hi> Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſight of God, when he had <hi>promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them no ſuch thing.</hi> And the internal with the external Righteouſneſs of godly ſincerity is called <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and <hi>the Righteouſneſs which is of God,</hi> partly becauſe it is of his <hi>inſtitution,</hi> and partly becauſe it is of his <hi>operation.</hi> It is the Righteouſneſs <hi>of God,</hi> becauſe it is of his <hi>inſtitution.</hi> He hath in and by the New Covenant ordained, That this ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted and taken for that Righteouſneſs
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101330:40"/>upon which he will accept men as Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and juſtifie them as ſuch againſt all condemnatory accuſations: This is his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and Revelation in the Goſpel, in which this <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> is ſaid to <hi>be revealed from faith to faith, Rom.</hi> 1.17. to wit, as that which is the object of Faith, or that which is to be believed to be the ſtated terms on which God will now juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and ſave men. And that it is meant of a Righteouſneſs inherent in men, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appears by the antitheſis in the next words, where on the contrary it's ſaid, <hi>the wrath of God is revealed from heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men;</hi> Where the ungodlineſs and <hi>unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of men,</hi> is put in oppoſition to the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Righteouſneſs of God alſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is of his <hi>operation</hi> and working in us. It is of his <hi>Creation,</hi> and therefore called the <hi>new Creature,</hi> the <hi>new man cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated after the Image of God in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true Holineſs,</hi> the <hi>Divine nature, begotten of God by the word of Truth, born, not of the will of man, or of the will of the fleſh, but of God.</hi> And it being of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and operation, it muſt needs be of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101330:41"/>his approbation too. This Evangelical Righteouſneſs is called the <hi>Righteouſneſs of God</hi> in the ſame ſenſe in which the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an life is called the <hi>life of God, Epheſ</hi> 4.18. not the life which he himſelf lives, but the life which he commands, and the life which by his Grace he enables men to live. As the Sacrament is called the Supper <hi>of the Lord,</hi> becauſe it is of his <hi>inſtitution:</hi> ſo is this inherent Righteouſneſs and Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by it, ſaid to be the Righteouſneſs <hi>of God</hi> for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>To reſtore fallen man to this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to acceptation with God and Juſtification thereby, and to render him capable of the happineſs deſigned him in another World, was the reaſon of ſending Chriſt into the World, and of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us, and of all the reſt of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory undertaking. For that I take to be the plain mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21
<note n="*" place="margin">(When I compare the foregoing verſes therewith, noting God's deſign of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling us to himſelf by Chriſt, which is done by an inward change of mind and will.)</note>. <hi>He hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him,</hi> that is, by means of him. Parallel to which is 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:101330:41"/>3.18. <hi>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſins, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This inherent Righteouſneſs is called the Righteouſneſs which is <hi>of God by Faith,</hi> becauſe it proceeds from God by the means of Faith, and not without it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. by believing that God will juſtifie and ſave men by Jeſus Chriſt in this way, and upon theſe terms of becoming inherently righteous, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, men come to be ſo, that they may be juſtified and ſaved.</p>
            <p>I have the rather given this brief Gloſs upon theſe Scriptures, becauſe I find Mr. <hi>Polhill</hi> ſtill, as others have done before him, will needs underſtand that this Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſs is meant of the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to us, and that it is called the Righteouſneſs <hi>of God,</hi> becauſe it is the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Chriſt, which is God,</hi> But methinks he and they ſhould conſider, that becauſe the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is the Righteouſneſs of him that is God as well as Man, that therefore it is nowiſe likely it ſhould ever be imputed to us any otherwiſe than in its bleſſed effects, and conſequently that which they ſurmiſe cannot be the ſenſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101330:42"/>of the Scriptures aforementioned. For as ſuch it is a <hi>mediatorial righteouſneſs,</hi> a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs reſulting from his conformity to the <hi>Law of his Mediation,</hi> which was a Law peculiar to himſelf alone. And it ſeems very rational to think this righteouſneſs no more communicable to us, otherwiſe than in its happy effects, than the acts and office of his Mediation are. And although, upon the account of its being ſo tranſcendent and glorious a righteouſneſs, it is a very great ground of conſolation and of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to us, that for the ſake of it our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical righteouſneſs will be accepted with God, and all our defects, ſo far as conſiſtent with ſincerity, freely pardoned, yet it is a great queſtion, whether it will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with Chriſtian modeſty to preſume our ſelves inveſted therewith, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than in the beneficial effects of it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs there were more ground for it than we can find in Scripture. We may well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think our ſelves, whether it be not a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment too rich and glorious for us to wear, and proper only for the perſon of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, the Son of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>If it ſhall yet be demanded, that if this be true, that we are juſtified upon account
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101330:42"/>of all other inherent Grace, as well as that of Faith, then how comes it to paſs that in Scripture Faith is ſtill ſaid to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for righteouſneſs, and not love or humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or the like? If there ſhould be no other reaſon but this, yet this might well ſatisfie us in this enquiry, <hi>viz.</hi> in that this Grace of Faith above any other, is in the nature of it <hi>adopted and fitted to ſubſerve God's deſign,</hi> in recovering us from the ſtate of ſin and miſery, into which we were ſunk, unto a ſtate of holineſs and happineſs, from which we were fallen.</p>
            <p>God's deſign was to <hi>reſtore us to happineſs by holineſs, and to make his own Grace glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the eyes of his Creatures in doing of it.</hi> And when you have well conſidered it, I think you will find that there is no one Grace or Vertue that could be ſo ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God in this deſign, as Faith: Nay, which is more, that thoſe Divine Vertues themſelves which conſtitute the New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Divine Nature (without which we are not capable of being made happy) could not have been introduced and brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the nature of fallen man, but by Faith. I will ſuppoſe that you cannot imagine, how God ſhould reſtore us to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101330:43"/>without reconciling us to himſelf, and being reconciled to us: Nor how he ſhould reconcile us to himſelf without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome Overtures of Grace to us: Nor how he ſhould be reconciled to us without our ſubmitting to his terms of Grace. And if not, I can eaſily ſhew you that we cannot be <hi>affected</hi> and wrought upon by God's <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture and offer</hi> of Grace, ſo as to anſwer his end in making it, <hi>nor ſubmit to,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with his terms of Grace without believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and conſequently that the execution of God's deſign in reſtoring us to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of glorifying the riches of his Grace therein, depends very much upon <hi>Faith,</hi> and more on that, than on any other Grace or Vertue whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We cannot be <hi>affected</hi> and wrought upon with God's <hi>offer</hi> of Grace, ſo as to give him the glory of it in thankful accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, due acknowledgments, and ſutable returns in loving him that ſhewed ſuch love to us, without this Grace of Faith. For the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of God's Grace in offering to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, through Chriſt, pardon, reſtauration to his favour, and ſalvation at laſt, upon condition of repentance, cannot <hi>enter</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of man, but by Faith. And the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:101330:43"/>reaſon hereof is, becauſe the offer of Grace, and the things offered by Grace, are matter of <hi>ſupernatural revelation,</hi> which do not further affect, than they are believed, as I ſhall farther ſhew in the next particular.</p>
            <p>But by believing that God of mere Grace in and by Chriſt hath promiſed pardon, acceptance into favour, the aſſiſtance of his Spirit, and eternal life unto Sinners (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe under condemnation) upon condition of repentance and a ſincere returning unto God; I ſay by this belief we come to truſt in, and rely upon that Grace, and on Chriſt as an All-ſufficient Saviour for thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed benefits, even in the performance of that Condition, and that in oppoſition to all opinion of meriting them by that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, or by any thing we can do. And it is by this belief and affiance that God receives from us the glory of his Grace, and Chriſt the honour of his performance for us: which anſwers one of the great ends deſigned by our recovery; for which cauſe it may very well be one reaſon why this Faith, rather than any other Grace, is ſaid to be imputed to us for Righteouſneſs. For we are told expreſly, <hi>that it is of Faith that it might be by Grace, Rom.</hi> 4.16. That
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101330:44"/>is, to cut off all pretence of merit, the ſame ſaving benefits are promiſed, and on the ſame Condition, to wit, that of Faith, to Heathen Idolaters, <hi>Sinners of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> as was to the ſtricteſt obſervers of the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> The reaſon in the cloſe of the verſe, gives that to be the meaning. And accordingly Faith, whether it be in one that hath been a great ſinner, or in one of a more inoffenſive life, hath God's Grace, not Man's merit, for its object on which it doth depend for all, and accordingly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes and aſcribes all to it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.15, 16. Which is one reaſon we ſee of God's ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of it to be the Condition, on which his great and precious promiſes are made, and may well be a reaſon alſo of his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it to men for Righteouſneſs when they do believe.</p>
            <p>For by the account we have why <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Faith was imputed to him for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, we have reaſon to believe that our giving to God the glory of his Grace and Goodneſs, Truth and Power, by this belief and affiance, and to Chriſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his undertaking, is of ſuch high acceptation with God, as that he of his goodneſs is pleaſed to honour and reward
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101330:44"/>it by imputing it to us for Righteouſneſs. For we ſee when <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith in God's promiſe, touching a numerous Iſſue, had nothing to lean upon but the Goodneſs, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity, and Power of God, and that theſe carried it with <hi>Abraham</hi> againſt all doubts and objections that might ariſe from the utmoſt humane and natural improbabilities of ever coming to paſs, ſo that <hi>he gave glory to God in being fully perſwaded, that what he had promiſed he was able alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form;</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath told us that <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> or for this very cauſe, <hi>his Faith was imputed to him for righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 4.21, 22.</p>
            <p>But the glorifying the riches of his Grace was not all that God had in deſign in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, but alſo the Renovation of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the reſtoring us to happineſs thereby: And Faith is as neceſſary and uſeful for the accompliſhing this part of God's deſign, as it was to effect the other, and therefore <hi>ſecondly,</hi> this may be another Reaſon why Faith is imputed for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and why it's ſaid to be ſo, rather than any other Grace.</p>
            <p>Without believing we cannot <hi>comply</hi> with the terms and condition on which Pardon
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:101330:45"/>and Salvation are promiſed, and without which they are not to be had, and that is in being renewed in our nature. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out believing thoſe Motives that tend to perſwade us to comply with, and ſubmit to the terms or condition, on which God for Chriſt's ſake hath promiſed to pardon us, to receive us into favour, and finally to ſave us, we can never actually comply with thoſe terms or that condition, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently without that can never be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving the benefits promiſed on that condition.</p>
            <p>For it is Faith, as it <hi>takes in thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> in their ſtrength and perſwaſive effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that becomes a vigorous and operative principle of all other Graces, Repentance, Love, Obedience, and the like, by which our nature becomes renewed: All which depend upon our believing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well may our Faith be named and put for all the reſt, as comprehending them in it, when it, rather than any other Grace, is ſaid to be imputed for Righteouſneſs. To make this evident, I ſhall ſuggeſt two things to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they are the great <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſpel, the Grace of God and Love of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:101330:45"/>Chriſt to loſt man, the good hoped for, and the evil feared, the good promiſed to thoſe that are good, and the evil threatned to thoſe that are evil, that <hi>operate</hi> upon the mind and will in men, to the producing that change in them, by which they become new men, ſincerely good men. <hi>If we love God, it is becauſe he loved us firſt,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19. If we <hi>live to Chriſt that died for us, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the love of Chriſt conſtrains us,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. If we <hi>are made partakers of a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, it is by the great and pretious promiſes that we are ſo,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>And 2. the <hi>operation</hi> of theſe <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſpel upon the mind <hi>depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our believing,</hi> and ſo conſequently do all thoſe happy effects in heart and life, which are produced by the operation of thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. For until the reality of thoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives are believed, they have <hi>no exiſtence</hi> or being in the Soul, and where they have no being they have <hi>no operation. The Word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with Faith in them that heard it, Heb.</hi> 4.2. The Love, Grace, and Favour of God to Sinners, in giving Chriſt for us, and of his Love in giving himſelf for us, and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promiſing us the benefit of pardon
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:101330:46"/>and ſalvation thereby only upon condition of our Repentance and Converſion unto God, being all of them things <hi>inviſible,</hi> and not objects of ſenſe, do not affect us, or perſwade us to repent, and in good earneſt turn to God, that we may be pardoned and ſaved, until we really <hi>believe</hi> theſe things. It is our Faith, or the credit we give to the Revelation which God hath made of theſe things, that gives them an exiſtence or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Soul, and upon that depends the efficacy and power of their prevailing with us to become new men. <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance or ſubſiſtence of things hoped for, and the evidence or conviction of things not ſeen, Heb.</hi> 11.1. Unleſs men firſt believe that God is ſo good, merciful, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to men, notwithſtanding they have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt him, as to pardon and ſave them, if they repent and become ſincerely obedient for the future, and not otherwiſe, they will never deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, when they are ſollicited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to gratifie the fleſh. Men muſt firſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him</hi> indeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will ſeek his Grace and Favour by becoming ſuch, and doing that upon which,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:101330:46"/>and not without which, he hath more or leſs declared his Grace and Favour is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and found. <hi>Without this Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> it is impoſſible to leave off thoſe things by which they have diſpleaſed him, and to betake themſelves to do thoſe things that are pleaſing in his ſight, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p>It was the belief that all good men had before the Law and under the Law, that God would <hi>keep Covenant and mercy with thoſe that love him and keep his Commandments,</hi> and not otherwiſe, that brought them ſo to love him and to keep his Commandments. It was their belief that <hi>there is forgiveneſs with him that he might be feared,</hi> as an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to men to fear him, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with them to fear him indeed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. It was the <hi>hope</hi> which even the Heathen <hi>Ninevites</hi> had (from the natural Notion they had of God, and from their obſervation of his general and common goodneſs to the World, notwithſtanding mens ſins) that if they did but repent and leave their ſins, forgiveneſs might poſſibly be obtained, that cauſed them to <hi>turn from their evil way, and from the violence that was in their hands, Jona.</hi> 3.8, 10.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:101330:47"/>
            <p>Now then, ſince ſo much as you ſee <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends</hi> upon <hi>Faith,</hi> as Repentance, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Regeneration, and all inherent Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Holineſs of living, there is great reaſon why it ſhould uſually be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as that which is imputed for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, rather than any other inherent Grace, and in the name, and as the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of all the reſt, as being the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive cauſe of them all.</p>
            <p>By the way you may obſerve then, that ſince it is as you ſee the Operation of the great <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſpel as believed, that in conjunction with the operation of the Holy Spirit effects that great Change in men, by which they become regularly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of all the bleſſedneſs of pardon and ſalvation which the Goſpel reveals, it muſt needs be very <hi>neceſſary</hi> for ſuch as you, who are miniſters of the Goſpel, to <hi>inſiſt</hi> much upon thoſe <hi>Motives</hi> in your diſcourſes to the people, and to inculcate and work them into their minds. To ſet life and death, heaven and hell before them, and to convince them of the reality of ſuch a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate, and of the <hi>inſeparable connexion</hi> that is between happineſs and their duty, and between a ſinful and hypocritical life,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:101330:47"/>and their eternal miſery. And to convince them that every one ſhall <hi>have</hi> in the next World according as he <hi>chuſeth</hi> in this, he that chuſeth the right <hi>way</hi> ſhall come to the right and beſt <hi>end,</hi> as he that chuſeth the wrong ſhall certainly come to the wrong and worſt, and that every he that ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh hereafter, is a ſelf murderer.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe to ſet in the peoples eye the <hi>preventing grace of God,</hi> what he hath already done for us, as a moſt affecting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive tending to reconcile us to him, and to think well of him, as of one that never ſought our ruin, but as pitying us, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king compaſſion on us, when we had brought it upon our ſelves, and not purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the advantage we have given him againſt us, nor revenging himſelf on us. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily contriving a way of our recovery from ſin, and from the miſery into which that hath brought us, yea, though it coſt him very dear to do it, in giving his Son to dye for us, when he could not otherwiſe do it with <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to himſelf in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the honour of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:101330:48"/>
            <p>Beſides, he hath done this for us men, and for our ſalvation, when he hath paſt by the fallen Angels: Chriſt the Son of God did not take hold of Angels, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Spirits, to reſcue them out of that deſtruction and miſery into which they plunged themſelves, and yet hath taken hold of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, to reſcue and pluck mankind out of the horrible pit of deſtruction, into which we were fallen, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>And now, is not all this Grace of God and Love of Chriſt, which thus far is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conditionate, and abſolutely free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought for on our part, and altogether an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent to any thing done by us to obtain it, a wonderful motive thankfully and joyfully to accept of thoſe moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gracious terms of our Recovery, which God in the Goſpel hath offered us?</p>
            <p>When it ſhall be conſidered, that God of his mere commiſeration and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards us, hath now tried us once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when we were all but as dead men before him, and hath put us in a way once again of being happy; with what face can we ſlight, deſpiſe, and abuſe ſuch
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:101330:48"/>Love by rejecting thoſe gracious terms of reconciliation, that were procured for us on ſuch coſtly terms as the ſufferings of the Son of God amount unto? But if we do, and after all this will perſiſt in our rebellion againſt Heaven, how can we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly expect that any other way or terms of pardon and ſalvation ſhould ever be offered unto us again? <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation,</hi> and ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully and freely offered us, and that on no harder conditions neither, than to ceaſe our wilful rebellion againſt God, and to become dutiful and loyal under his eaſie yoke and gentle Government by the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Law? <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p>If then ſuch mighty Motives as the Love of God, and his Son Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, ſo wonderfully expreſt, and the hope of Heaven, and the fear of Hell, will not work upon us to repent, to change our minds, and amend our lives, and to become new Creatures; what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Motives, think we, can God uſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men by? Doubtleſs they are theſe Motives will do it, if any thing will do it: and for that reaſon they ſhould (as I ſaid) be inſiſted on by thoſe, whoſe ſpecial bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101330:49"/>appointed them by God is to win Souls.</p>
            <p>And as theſe Motives ſhould be much and often inculcated upon the minds of the people for the reaſon aforeſaid, ſo for the ſame reaſon they ſhould be managed with all the advantage, in reſpect of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, that can be thought on, to reach their end, in operating powerfully upon the people's Souls. Such for one is <hi>plaineſs of ſpeech,</hi> as the phraſe is, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. and not as <hi>Moſes,</hi> who put a vail over his face. By which plainneſs of ſpeech (if it be what I mean) things are fitted and prepared for the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and capacity of the meaneſt, whoſe ſalvation God hath deſigned as much as the ſalvation of the more learned and wiſe. If <hi>Peter</hi> will expreſs his love to his Maſter indeed, he muſt as well ſeed his Lambs as his Sheep, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15.</p>
            <p>And by how much the more matters ſo affecting in themſelves, as the Motives of the Goſpel are, are delivered with an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſe, ſeriouſneſs</hi> and <hi>gravity,</hi> by ſo much the more they will command atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſideration from the people, and the ſooner <hi>ſink down into their hearts,</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:101330:49"/>and the more powerfully operate upon the mind and will.</p>
            <p>And if the experience of many (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom I number my ſelf) be of any conſideration in place of proof, then the <hi>intermixing Scripture Texts</hi> in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Diſcourſes, aptly applyed, and wiſely managed, is much more edifying to the people, than ſuch Diſcourſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that can be, though otherwiſe for the matter of them, they may be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scripture. For beſides that ſo doing greatly helps memory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the matter, without which the operation of the matter vaniſheth with the matter it ſelf: And beſides alſo the benefit of growing thereby into better acquaintance with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Mine of theſe Motives of which I ſpeak, and of becoming able by uſe to reduce ſcattered Texts of one and the ſame import to heads of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; I ſay beſides all this, and more which might be ſaid, it tends greatly to <hi>bind</hi> the matter delivered the faſter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conſcience, when it ſhall come ſo viſibly armed with authority from
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:101330:50"/>Heaven, as by that means it does; and when the Laws and Statutes of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall be produced, laid open, and urged to make it good and enforce it. The Scriptures themſelves will be found of more authority in the Conſciences of men, than the beſt words men can ſpeak, though never ſo rational and true. In a word, as <hi>Apollos</hi> was a man <hi>mighty in the Scriptures,</hi> ſo he <hi>mightily convinced</hi> his hearers <hi>by the Scriptures, Acts</hi> 18.24, 28. I need not mention unto you how much it was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s manner to reaſon out of the Scriptures of the old Teſtament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe of the New were in being, when he had to do with thoſe that own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.2. and 28.23. Nor how our Lord Chriſt himſelf collected and brought together the things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, which were ſcattered up and down in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and expounded them to his Diſciples, and thereby opened their underſtandings, and cauſed their hearts to burn within them; and that, I think, is not unlike the operation of the Motives of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel I have been ſpeaking of, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.27, 32, 45, 46.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:101330:50"/>
            <p>There is one thing more which I muſt add to obviate an objection; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to explain and confirm ſomething I have aſſerted. I know ſome, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps your ſelf, will be ready to object, That the tenour of my reaſoning touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God's imputing Faith it ſelf, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inherent Grace for Righteouſneſs in juſtifying men, tends to confound Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Sanctification, and to make them all one. But that follows not at all: For Sanctification is the conſtituting or making men Evangelically righteous or holy by the joint operation of God's Holy Spirit, and the Evangelical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; but Juſtification is God's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing or declaring them, as he doth in the Goſpel, to be righteous according to the terms of the Goſpel, as having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the condition upon which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of Sin and eternal Life are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in promiſed.</p>
            <p>Juſtification is a Juridical act of God as Judge, which doth not make a man righteous as ſanctification doth, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tryal pronounceth him to be ſo, and by it the perſon tried is acquited and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:101330:51"/>diſcharged from the accuſation of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, impenitency, and wilful diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Goſpel, and ſo alſo from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation it ſelf. So that Juſtification is not Sanctification, but ſuppoſeth it as antecedent thereunto, at leaſt in order of nature. <hi>Whom he called them he alſo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, and whom he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them he alſo glorified, Rom.</hi> 8.30. He doth not ſay, whom he juſtified them he alſo ſanctified, but them alſo he glorified. Sanctification is not brought in between Juſtification and Glorification in that golden Chain, but is placed in order as going before both in effectual cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>The other thing I would add for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation and confirmation is this: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have ſaid that the Faith which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for Righteouſneſs, is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of Repentance and Obedience to the Goſpel: Now leaſt you ſhould not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied therewith, I ſhall give you this plain account why we cannot reaſonably underſtand otherwiſe. For the Scripture doth exclude ſuch from ſharing in the ſaving benefits of the Covenant, as are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:101330:51"/>impenitent, unregenerate, and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. And if ſo, then no man can ſhare in thoſe ſaving benefits, whereof Juſtification is one, until his Faith doth produce Repentance, Regeneration, and Obedience, unleſs you will ſuppoſe that which no man does, that theſe are no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffects of Faith, For he that believes is born of God, is to a degree renewed to his likeneſs, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>And when I ſay thus, I am not of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that men cannot be juſtified un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they have fulfilled ſome time in a courſe of holy living and new obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, internal and external. But when a man ſo believes, as that ſuch a real change is thereby wrought in the heart, as is the beginning of a new life for the preſent, and the foundation of a holy life for the future, then undoubtedly he paſſeth out of an unjuſtified into a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſtate. This change in the mind and will by means of Faith, doth firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a man a good man; and when this change firſt takes place, then God's <hi>Laws</hi> are firſt <hi>put into the mind, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:101330:52"/>written in the heart,</hi> upon which God promiſeth in the New Covenant <hi>to be our God, and that we ſhall be his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that he will be merciful to our unrighteouſneſs, and our ſins and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to remember no more, Hebr.</hi> 8.10, 12. and 10.16, 17.</p>
            <p>And it is obſervable, that the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication upon which God in the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant here mentioned, promiſeth to be our God, and to forgive our ſins, is not mentioned under the Name or Notion of Faith or Believing, but of having the Divine Laws put into the mind, and written in the heart. Which would be ſomewhat ſtrange, if this writing the Law in the heart were no part of the Condition, without which God will not vouchſafe unto any man that great benefit of the Covenant, Juſtification.</p>
            <p>There is no doubt indeed, but that though Faith be not here mentioned, yet it is ſuppoſed and implyed, in as much as without it the Law cannot be written in the heart in the ſenſe we ſpeak of it now.</p>
            <p>But then, when at other times Faith only is mentioned, as that which quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101330:52"/>men for Juſtification, and as the Condition of the promiſe of Pardon and Salvation, yet then this writing of the Law in the heart is alſo to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. For it is not to be imagined, that the putting of the Law into the mind, and writing it in the heart, would be mentioned in a deſcription of the tenour of the New Covenant, as that qualification upon which God will be our God, take us for his people, and forgive our ſins, (which imply Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) if any Faith, or Faith in any reſpect ſhort of producing this effect, would be available and ſufficient unto Juſtification.</p>
            <p>It's true, the Scripture in ſome places tells us that Faith is imputed for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, without telling us what, or what manner of Faith this is: But then in other places it is plainly deſcribed to us by the nature of its operation, as that <hi>it purifieth the heart,</hi> Acts 15.9. <hi>worketh by love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. <hi>overcometh the world,</hi> 1 John 5.4. and <hi>ſanctifieth the whole man,</hi> Acts 26.18.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:101330:53"/>
            <p>We ſee then, that the inſeparable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Faith, as here the writing of the Law in the heart, are ſometimes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as thoſe things which qualifie us for the bleſſing of the Covenant, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Faith it ſelf only. But if we will take the whole teſtimony of the Scriptures together, we ſhall find that both are intended: And why then ſhould we contend, as ſome do, about dividing theſe in qualifying us for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, as parts of that Evangelical Righteouſneſs which will be imputed to us for Righteouſneſs?</p>
            <p>After all this, let me tell you, Sir, That there is a ſenſe in which it is not diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scripture, to ſay that a man is juſtified by ſuch acts of Evangelical Righteouſneſs or Obedience, as do not take place till long after he firſt believes, and believes to Juſtification. And thus <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s believing, mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. which was not until ſome years after he firſt believed, is ſaid to be imputed to him for Righteouſneſs. And many years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that again he was juſtified by yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience to God's Command about
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101330:53"/>offering his Son, <hi>James</hi> 2.21. And ſomewhat of like nature is alſo ſaid of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, Heb.</hi> 11.7. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9, 22.</p>
            <p>But theſe things are ſaid, I conceive, in reference to the continuance of their Juſtification, and not to their Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at firſt. For as thoſe acts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, repenting, &amp;c. which do firſt conſtitute a man a new Creature, are at firſt imputed to him for Righteouſneſs, ſo all after-acts of Evangelical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and of Faith it ſelf are ſtill impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for Righteouſneſs to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of his Juſtification. To which agrees that reading of <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.11. which runs thus, <hi>let him that is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous be juſtified ſtill;</hi> and <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God is revealed from faith to faith,</hi> Rom. 1.17.</p>
            <p>But otherwiſe, <hi>if the righteous turneth away from his</hi> Righteouſneſs, <hi>and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth iniquity, and doth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, all the Righteouſneſs which he hath done ſhall not be mentioned: In his treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs which he hath treſpaſſed, and in his ſin that he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:101330:54"/>die,</hi> Ezek. 18.24. Again, <hi>when I ſay to the righteous he ſhall ſurely live; if he truſt to his own Righteouſneſs</hi> (i. e. his former Righteouſneſs) <hi>and commit iniquity, all his Righteouſneſs ſhall not be remembred,</hi> Ezek. 33.13. <hi>Now the juſt ſhall live by faith, but if he draw back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him,</hi> Hebr. 10.38. If then you do but conſider upon what terms men are at firſt juſtified, and upon what terms they continue to be ſo afterwards, you will eaſily perceive it to be a great and moſt important truth to ſay, That we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by believing and obeying the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, Sir, which I have thus done by way of Eſſay, without regard to method, I ſubmit to your conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I know right-well it's in vain, if I had a mind to it (which yet I am far from) to impoſe upon you, or to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to receive any thing for truth farther than it brings it's evidence to be ſo along with it. And it were to wiſhed that every one were able to diſcern
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:101330:54"/>when it doth ſo: But that's a thing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be deſired, than expected in this our preſent ſtate in this World. But it's Argument enough to treat one another ſo almoſt as if we did, if we have not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent reaſon to think we are but inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and diſſembling friends to Truth, and love it not for it ſelf, nor any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than it will accommodate us in ſome ſecular or carnal reſpect or other: and it is not eaſie to determine when we have apparent reaſon ſo to think. And therefore I conclude it ſafeſt for our ſelves rather to err in treating one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our differences better than we deſerve, than worſe. And ſo to do is better for them alſo that differ from us, ſo far as they differ from Truth; yea, and better for the Truth it ſelf too. For it is often ſeen, that when a prejudice is taken up againſt the perſons of men, be the Cauſe never ſo juſt, the Truth it ſelf is the leſs eſteemed, if not ſhrewdly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, becauſe held by them; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when its evidence is not written as with a Sun beam. So that when we, by an undue behaviour in pleading the Cauſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:101330:55"/>of Truth, draw upon our ſelves diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from them whom we would draw from Errour, we prevaricate in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and act croſs to our own deſign: A thing which ſome engaged in Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies have been to blame in.</p>
            <p>However, it will be our wiſdom in reading of Books of this nature to mind the Argument, and to take little notice of any unbecoming girds or reflections, unleſs it be to bewail them, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to follow, as indeed there is need, that ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>let him that readeth underſtand, Mark</hi> 13.14. Thus deſiring, that you and I, and all other Chriſtians, may ſpeak the truth in love, in love both to it and men, and receive it in the love of it, that we may be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted by it, I take my leave, and remain as ever,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt affectionately to ſerve you in all offices of Chriſtian love and reſpect,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 22. 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:101330:55"/>
            <head>Books printed for, and ſold by <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the Biſhop's-head in St, <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <p>H. <hi>Mori Opera Theologica,</hi> Folio. Price 1 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s Reply to a late Anſwer to his Antidote againſt Idolatry, with the Appendix, Octavo. Price 4<hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Spencer <hi>diſſertatio de Urim &amp; Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim,</hi> Octavo. Price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Frederici Loſſi <hi>Obſervationes Medici,</hi> Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epigrammata</hi> Juvenilia <hi>in quatuor par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes diviſa, Encomia, Seria, Satyras &amp; Jocoſa, per</hi> Guilielmum Speed. Price bound 9 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Smyth</hi>'s unjuſt man's doom: as exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the ſeveral kinds of Juſtice, and their obligation, with a particular repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of Injuſtice, and danger of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Conformity, Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Smyth</hi>'s two Sermons at the Aſſizes in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hallywell</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Chriſtianity, Octavo. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> —Account of Familiſm, as it is revived, and propagated by the Quakers, Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101330:56"/>
            <p>Some Opinions of Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a ſecond Dialogue between <hi>Philau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Breerwood</hi>'s Enquiries into the Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of Languages, Octav. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Stop to the Courſe of Separation, or the Separation of the new Separatiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Libertas Eccleſiaſtica,</hi> by <hi>Will. Falkner,</hi> Octavo. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Myſtery of Iniquity unfolded, or the falſe Apoſtles and the Authors of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery compared, in their Secular Deſign, and means of accompliſhing it, by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the Chriſtian Religion, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of promoting it, Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and our Union and Communion with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Defence and Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Diſcourſe concerning the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Communion with him, with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reſpect to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Charge of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſm and Pelagianiſm, Oct. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Webſter's</hi> Hiſtory of Metals, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:101330:56"/>is declared the ſigns of Ores and Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals both before and after digging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quarto. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Duty of Self. Reſignation to the Divine Will: By the late Pious and Learned <hi>John Worthington,</hi> D.D. Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to us, and our Sins to him, with many uſeful queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereunto pertaining, Reſolved. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Reflections more at large up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what hath been publiſhed concerning that Subject, by Mr. <hi>Robert Ferguſon</hi> in his Intereſt of Reaſon in Religion; and by Dr. <hi>John Owen</hi> in his Book ſtiled <hi>Communion with God.</hi> By <hi>Tho. Hotchkis,</hi> Oct. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Ferguſon</hi>'s Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place book, in 2 Letters, Quart. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Comparative Anatomy of Trunks, together with an account of their Vegita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion grounded thereupon; In 2 Parts: The former read before the <hi>R. Society, Feb.</hi> 25. 1674/5. the latter, <hi>June</hi> 17. 1675. the whole explicated by ſeveral Figures in 19 Copper-plates; preſented to the <hi>R. S.</hi> in the years 1673. and 1674. by <hi>Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah Grew,</hi> M. D. and Fellow of the <hi>R. S.</hi> in Octavo. Price 4 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
